<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Quakers confuted, being an answer unto nineteen queries; propounded by them, and sent to the elders of the church of Duckenfield in Cheshire; wherein is held forth much of the doctrine and practise concerning revelations, and immediate voices, and against the holy Scriptures, Christs ministry, churches and ordinances &amp;c. Together with an answer to a letter which was written and sent by one of them to a family of note and quality in the said county, which pleaded for perfection in this life, and for quaking. By Samuel Eaton, teacher of the Church of Christ heretofore meeting at Duckenfield, now in Stockport in Cheshire.</title>
            <author>Eaton, Samuel, 1596?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 207 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82555</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E719_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9865</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873623</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873623</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166753</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82555)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166753)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 111:E719[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Quakers confuted, being an answer unto nineteen queries; propounded by them, and sent to the elders of the church of Duckenfield in Cheshire; wherein is held forth much of the doctrine and practise concerning revelations, and immediate voices, and against the holy Scriptures, Christs ministry, churches and ordinances &amp;c. Together with an answer to a letter which was written and sent by one of them to a family of note and quality in the said county, which pleaded for perfection in this life, and for quaking. By Samuel Eaton, teacher of the Church of Christ heretofore meeting at Duckenfield, now in Stockport in Cheshire.</title>
                  <author>Eaton, Samuel, 1596?-1665.</author>
                  <author>Waller, Richard, d. 1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 79, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. White for Thomas Brewster, and are to be sold at the sign of the three Bibles at the West-end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Thomason received his copy in November 1653.</note>
                  <note>Includes: A coppy of a letter which Richard Waller a Quaker, sent to a gentelmans family, near Stockport in Chesire.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "1653 Nou. 18."; 4 in imprint date crossed out and altered to "3".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166753:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Quakers Confuted, <hi>BEING</hi> AN ANSWER Vnto Nineteen QUERIES; Propounded by them, and ſent to the <hi>Elders</hi> of the Church of <hi>Duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenfield</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEREIN</hi> Is held forth much of the Doctrine and practiſe Concerning Revelations, and immediate Voices, and againſt the holy Scriptures, Chriſts Miniſtry, Churches and Ordinances <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>TOGETHER</hi> With an Anſwer to a Letter which was Written and ſent by one of them to a Family of Note and Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the ſaid County, which pleaded for perfection in this life, and for Quaking.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Samuel Eaton,</hi> Teacher of the Church of Chriſt hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore meeting at <hi>Duckenfield,</hi> now in <hi>Stockport</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. White</hi> for <hi>Thomas Brewſter,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſign of the three Bibles at the Weſt-end of <hi>Pauls. 165<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:166753:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:166753:2"/>
            <head>To the Supream Authority of the Nation, the <hi>Parliament</hi> now ſitting in <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the Duty of all that Love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in Sincerity, to contend for the Faith that was once given to the Saints, every man in his place, according to the Calling, Office, Power, Intereſt, Gift, Ability that he hath received from God. And I in my place (though the weakeſt of many, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yet led forth thereto by ſpecial inviting Providences) have done it both formerly and at preſent. And I Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the boldneſs to preſent my poor, plain, weak and ſlender labours to your Honors view, and moſt humbly beg your favorable conſtruction of my deſign and ſcope in them. It is not to aſperſe any who are innocent; it is not to bring Saints who are weak and frail under con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelie; Neither is it to exaſperate the Supream Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate againſt any Perſons in whom the viſibility of Saintſhip ſhall be found; Nor is it to conivnce theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (betwixt whom and my ſelf the conteſt lies) of their Errour; for had there been any hope of that, I ſhould have found out another way; but it is to preſerve thoſe who are yet ſound in the Faith from infection, and it is to awaken others (who are far more able in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures
<pb facs="tcp:166753:3"/> then my ſelf) to appear for God, for Chriſt, and for the Truth, in ſuch times of the great Apoſtaſie of ſo very many from the Faith. And it is to provoke your Honors to a ſelf-reflection, if thereby you may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcern what your own Duty may be, and whether there be not ſomewhat which the Supream Magiſtrate, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Power, Place and Intereſt is called to do, in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to that command. I know you will manifeſt very much tenderneſs to all Saints, though in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent forms, and of different judgements in circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Truths, and no queſtion Chriſt will take it kindly from your hands; but there is a company of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate Chriſtians who are diſperſed all over the Land, and who do ſow much corrupt ſeed (which comes up with great increaſe in many places) who yet do paſs with ſome for precious Saints. But my hope is, and my Prayer ſhall be, that the Lord will make you wiſe to judg ef Saintſhip according to Scriptural Rules, and not according to the large Charity of ſome who are truly good, though too much friends to them. You are not ignorant what a Character Chriſt himſelf gives of falſe Teachers, though appearing a Righteous, Innocent and Harmleſs People, (as theſe Quakers ſtile them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) he calls them Wolves in Sheeps clothing. And</hi> Paul <hi>ſpeaking of ſuch, compares them to Satan in this, That they will transform themſelves (as he doth himſelf into an Angel of Light, ſo they) into Miniſters of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. And</hi> John <hi>in his Epiſtles makes them all Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts, And the Scope &amp; Drift of all the Apoſtles in all their Epiſtles almoſt, is to confirm the Faith which the Saints had received, and to preſerve from, &amp; recover them out of Errour; and it is to impugn ſuch Doctrine as</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:166753:3"/> 
               <hi>Seducers brought in among them, &amp; the Zeal that they ſhewed is worthy of obſervation. You know alſo that as God is a righteous God, &amp; loves Righteouſneſs, and therefore if you advance Righteouſneſs (as my hope in God is that you wil) you ſhall not loſe your reward; For he is alſo a jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous God in the things wherein his Glory is more immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately concerned; And his Honor is not more concerned in any thing then it is in the Doctrines which men hold and teach, and in the Worſhips which men give to him: therefore if you alſo ſhew your ſelves jealous of his Glory in theſe things, it will be aſſuredly written down in Gods Book of Remembrance what Zeal you had for your God, and the Lord will bleſs you thence forward. Are Magiſtrates for a Praiſe to good works, and for a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour to evil works, while only they are good and evil, but when they come to be beſt or worſt (as they alwayes be when Religion is in them) is it ſo that they then have nothing to do, neither are they to meddle with them? If this be the ſenſe of the Apoſtles words (as all Perſons which do exclude the Magiſtrate from having any thing to do with the matters of God) will have it to be; it is a ſtrange one, and hath nothing to bear it up, either from that Text, or any that I know of. But you are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently inſtructed (I doubt not) concerning your own pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and your Zeal ſhewed where the honour of God is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, will provoke many whereto they will the rather be carried, conſidering that no ſins do bring more &amp; greater plagues upon a Nat on that profeſſeth Righteouſneſs, then ſins againſt the firſt Table do; Now Magiſtrates are the Fathers of the Commonwealth, and therefore ſhould ſtudy to preſerve it from thoſe judgments that would deſtroy it. Or elſe why are Laws made againſt Oaths, and ſuch kind</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:166753:4"/> 
               <hi>of Blaſphemies, if they be not to intermedle with matters of the firſt Table; and are there no ſins againſt the firſt Table that God hates ſo much as he hates Oaths? yea, there are Blaſphemies of opinion that are of a more hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and harrid nature. But what ought to be done in this caſe, I leave that to your Honors wiſdom to find out by ſearching of the Scriptures; knowing that the Lord hath made many of you very dextrous and skilful in the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Scripture. When you meet with Crimes of a Civil Nature mentioned in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as Murther, Adultery, Theft, &amp;c. You cannot Read their Penalties there which ought to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted; you find the ſins, but not the Puniſhments againſt ſuch Offenders; What courſe do you take? you are forced to fly to the Old Teſtament, and to fetch your Light thence. There are Apoſtates from the true God, from the true Chriſt, from the true Faith in the great Fundamental of it, and from the true Worſhip in the very Subſtantials of it, and who alſo are Teachers of Apoſtaſie, who yet were once enlightned, and knew the Truth; What ought to be done to ſuch, or what courſe ought to be taken, that Diſhonour to God may not be increaſed, nor the Land troubled by Gods Controverſie againſt it? I leave it to be ſeriouſly thought of; and I hope the Lord will guide your minds (among the multiplicity of other weighty and ſerious thoughts within you) to the ſeaſonable conſideration of it. But if there be Sorcery and Familiarity with the Devil to be found among a People, who challenge Propriety in God, excluding all others from Intereſt in him; I have no cauſe to doubt but that ſuch groſs polluting Evils will be ſearched out.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:166753:4"/> 
               <hi>The God of Wiſdom direct, and guide your Honors in all things that you take in hand, that by well doing, you may gain the Teſtimony of the Saints and World, that you are raiſed up of God, to exalt God, Chriſt, Faith, Truth, Godlineſs, Righteouſneſs, and Mercy in this Nation. I moſt humbly beg pardon from your Honours, for my boldneſs in ſuggeſting theſe thoughts of my heart, and ſpreading them before you, and remain</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honors in all humble Duty</hi> Samuel Eaton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:166753:5"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian READER, about three years ſince I was travelling through <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ham</hi> towards <hi>London,</hi> and meeting with many reports reſpecting a People who are called Quakers, concerning Sorcery and witchcraft that ſhould be among them; for confirmation whereof, it was aſſerted, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Perſons who came among them only as ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Obſervators of their way, grew diſtemper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and fell into trances among them. I was very deſirous to ſatisfie my ſelf concerning the truth thereof, being very unwilling to entertain reports upon Hear-ſay; At laſt (about half a mile from <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham</hi> Town) I met with a man of a godly, ſober ſpirit (as he appeared to me) &amp; Preacher to a people about amile off from the aforementioned Town: up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on occaſion of enquiring of the way which I was to go, I fell into diſcourſe with him about the Quakers, and asked him, whether he conceived that there was any Sorcery among them; he anſwered, yea; and thereupon made Relation of this enſuing Story. <hi>There is (ſaid he) a young man of my Fariſh, whom I judge to be truly godly; he deſired leave from me to go among them one day to behold their way: but I durſt not give way unto him, but told him that is might be a
<pb facs="tcp:166753:5"/> tempting of God if he ſhould go. Notwithſtanding (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to me) he went, and while he was obſerving of them, he began to be ſick, and was afraid he ſhould fall, and wiſhed himſelf from among them, and ſoon after their meeting was ended; and he grew well again, and remained unſatiſfied with that which he had ſeen (for he came late) and was very deſirous to have ſome further knowledge of their way, and therefore went the ſecond time among them; and after he had been there awhile, he began to be ſick again, and his diſtemper increaſed upon him, till at length he fell into a trance among them, in which they left him, and went their way; and when he came to himſelf there was onely an old woman there, and he returned home, and was very ſenſible of his miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriage in not hearkening to my advice, and came to me and confeſſed his fault, and acquainted me with all that he had done, and what had befallen him, and bleſſed himſelf from that people, and concluded the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil was powerful among them.</hi> Having received this Relation from the Miniſter (who was a meer Stranger to me, but very godly in all his expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) I became credulous of many like things, which I had before that time heard of them, and thought to have nothing to do with that Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men; and though I have been often ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited to confer with them, yet I have perpetually declined it, becauſe I looked upon them as a People not onely deluded, but given over to the power of Satan. Notwithſtanding beyond all mine own thoughts, I have (by the Providence of the Lord, which orders all things) been called forth to have ſome dealings with them, and am now in a ſort
<pb facs="tcp:166753:6"/> neceſſitated to appear in Print againſt them. Fo thus it fell out.</p>
            <p>There was a certain man, named <hi>Richard Waller,</hi> who was Servant at a Gentlemans Houſe near <hi>Stopport</hi> in Cheſhire; this man fell in league with a Woman ſervant in the ſame houſe with him, who ſtood related to us, and was a Member of our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; ſhe acquainted us with this league, and ſought our conſent; we appeared not againſt it ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, becauſe he made ſome profeſſion of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but withheld our conſent till he ſhould clear himſelf from ſome ſcandalous fact that was charged upon him; but ſhe was impatient of delay, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his own relation of the thing, and to our grief and trouble gave herſelf up unto him in Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age. Not long after both of them left the Family in which they lived, and went into the lower parts of Lancaſhire to live there, near unto thoſe parts where there are many Quakers, who meet frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together. This man (it ſeems) had not been long there but he fell in among them, and gave himſelf up unto them; and within a ſhort time after writ a Letter to the Family (where he and his wife had ſo lately been Servants) in which he pleads for ſuch a Perfection which excludes all ſin from being committed by the Saints; and he alſo pleads for quaking, and produces many Scriptures to prove both; and he reviles Miniſters under the Title of Prieſts of this World which teach deceit, and he denies all the Teachers of the World, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth his Teacher to be within him, and he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts them to wait upon the Lord, and to ceaſe
<pb facs="tcp:166753:6"/> from man, and to mind the Light of God-within them, with much more of this nature. A Copy of this Letter was given unto me, which I communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the Brethren, and after a debate had of thoſe two things, which he aſſerted and endevour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make out by Scripture; it was concluded that the Letter with thoſe Scriptures ſhould be anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſent to this mans wife who wrote the Letter, for the eſtabliſhing of her, becauſe ſhe ſtood rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us, and we were ſenſible of the danger that ſhe was in; and I was intreated to draw the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, which I did, and it was ſent by a ſpecial Maſſenger unto her. About two Moneths after, the ſame man that wrote the Letter (which occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned our Letter of anſwer to his wife) came over to our ſide as a Meſſenger ſent by the Quakers, with a Reply to our Anſwer, and with a paper of nineteen Queſtions; and upon the fifth of <hi>June</hi> laſt, being the firſt day of the Week, he delivers the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Queſtions in their name to me, in the face of the Congregation, and requires an anſwer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and pleads for an Abſolute Perfection in the preſence of all that were aſſembled; the paper of Reply he kept back, as being too ſcurrilous in his own thoughts, as ſome collected that ſpake with him; but I had notice of it, and called for it from him the next day, and then received it.</p>
            <p>Upon this account it is that I come to be engaged in an anſwer to theſe Queries; I have alſo annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Copy of his Letter that was given me, and the Anſwer which I ſent unto it, which was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to his wife, together with the Reply that
<pb facs="tcp:166753:7"/> the Quakers made unto it; which indeed is too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to be read of any who have moſt time; it is ſuch a ſottiſh and ſenſeleſs piece of ſtuff, and hath ſo much ſcurrilous language in it. But by it, and by the Queries, the Saints and World may know what a people theſe are, &amp; what little hope there is of any good to be wrought upon them; if they would admit of any rational diſcourſe from Scripture, ſome encouragement would be given to ſpend time that way with them; but they can eaſily evade all with ſuch Anſwer as this, <hi>Buſie minds give ſenſes to Scripture, and are Perſons that have nothing to do with Scripture, can witneſs nothing of that they ſpeak of.</hi> They pretend to ſpeak and act all by the Spirit, and if any one will try the Spirit that they ſpeak by, their Reply is, that <hi>ſuch an one can neither witneſs Scripture nor Spirit,</hi> and therefore hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with ſuch things. Yet they deceive many, and they increaſe in number continually; but the time will come that they ſhall proceed no further. In the mean time it ought to be ſad to every godly ſpirit, that Satan ſhould have ſuch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to work ſo effectually in and upon many who have been reputed Saints, who are drawn into them; but God will iſſue all to his Glory at the laſt, and in this I reſt, and remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord Jeſus</hi> Samuel Eaton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div type="queries">
               <pb facs="tcp:166753:7"/>
               <head>THE Quakers QUERIES, For ſome Friends who call themſelves Elders of the Church of Chriſt, meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Stopport,</hi> theſe &amp;c. A few <hi>Queries</hi> to you who profeſs your ſelves to be Teachers, Paſtors and Elders.</head>
               <p>Querie 1. <hi>WHether you have the ſame eternal Spirit which gave forth the Scriptures, yea or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 2. <hi>Whether the Apoſtles did give a right meak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scriptures when they gave them forth, or left them to you to give a meaning to them, yea or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 3. <hi>Whether the Plagues be not added to them who add to the Propheſies written in the Book? and whether his Name be not diminiſhed out of the Book of Life, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhes? and whether you can witneſs this Name, yea or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 4. <hi>Whether you have an infallible Judgement to judge of things eternal, yea or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 5. <hi>Whether you be above the Apoſtle, and are able to judge his Condition? becauſe you ſay, he was not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, who ſaid, he ſpoke wiſdom among them that were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 6. <hi>Whether you have the hidden wiſdom which God</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:166753:8"/> 
                  <hi>ordained before the World was, which the Apoſtle speaks of yea or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 7. <hi>Whether you have heard the voice of the live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God of Heaven and Earth? or whether do you not take the Prophets words, Chriſts words, and the Apoſtles words, and ſay, he ſaith it, when ſaith the Lord, I never ſpoke to you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 8. <hi>Whether a man ſhall overcome the body of ſin while he is upon the Earth, yea or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 9. <hi>Whether you preach no other Doctrine then that which the Apoſtles did? that which was from the beginning, which we have heard, which we have ſeen with our eyes, which we have looked upon, and with our hands have handled of the word of life? For this life is made manifeſt, and we have ſeen it, and bear witneſs and ſhew it unto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 10. <hi>Whether you have this word which was from the beginning, and this life manifeſted to you which was to the Apoſtles? And if it be, why do you take a Text from the Letter, and Preach from it, and ſhew the People the Letter?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 11. <hi>And ſhew me where the Prophets did take a Text, and preach from it, but only Chriſt read a place, and ſaid, it was fulfilled, who ſaid he was anointed to preach; and which of you can witneſs you are anointed to preach by the living God, yea or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 12. <hi>Tell me why you ſing</hi> Davids <hi>Conditions and Experiences in Meeter, and when you read them, hats you keep on, and when you ſing them, hats you put off.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 13. <hi>Whether you have the voice, and whether you do know the voice of Chriſt from the voice of a Stranger? My Sheep know my voice, ſaith Chriſt, ſeing that you are ſo forward to judge, and ſit as Judges of the Saints Conditions?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 14. <hi>Whether that which is in you which Judgeth, be eternal and infallible, yea or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 15. <hi>What is the Ordinance which is ordained of God, that thoſe which you call Quakers deny, and where or when did God command you to obſerve them? As to sprinkle Infants, to pray before and after your Sermons, as you call them, or to ſet times, dayes and hours, which was in the Generation which were enemies to Chriſt, who obſerved ſuch things.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:166753:8"/>
               <p>Querie 16. <hi>What theſe Ordinances of God be which you speak of? And where God commanded them, and to whom, which you ſay thoſe that you call Quakers do deny? mention them in particular, and declare them openly in Writing, and give over accuſing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 17. <hi>Whether you do not ſeduce the People to draw them from the anointing within them? when as</hi> John <hi>ſaith, they need no man teach them, but as the anointing, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe was Eternal Life to him that did abide in the anointing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 18. <hi>Whether you do not bewitch the people, to draw them from the Spirit of God within them, to obſerve theſe things which God never commanded; to tell people of a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and following your outward Teaching, who ſtand pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing in the Synagogues, and are called of men-Maſters; which Chriſt did forbid,</hi> Mat. 23. <hi>And have the chiefeſt places in the Aſſemblies; Whether theſe be not Antichriſts, which act contrary to the Commands of Chriſt, this yea or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Querie 19. <hi>Whether a man ſhall ever grow up that he need no man teach him under your Miniſtry, yea or no? ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtle ſaith, you need no man teach you, and you which have been long Teachers, how many have you brought up into this Condition?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Church of Chriſt is the Pillar and Ground of Truth, which doth witneſs the eternal Spirit; and if you be the ſame Church, and have the ſame Spirit, Anſwer me theſe Queries without any conſequences or ſenſes, otherwiſe deny your El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſhip and Paſtorſhip, and to be no Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From ſome Friends in the Truth in</hi> Lancaſhire, <hi>whom the World calls</hi> Quakers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answers_to_queries">
               <pb facs="tcp:166753:9"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:166753:9"/>
               <head>An ANSWER to the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Queries,</hi> brought by one <hi>Richard Waller</hi> a Meſſenger of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and preſented by him in the name of them, unto the Elders of the Church common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called the Church of <hi>Duckenfield,</hi> now meeting at <hi>Stockport</hi> in the face and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the whole Congregation; and an Anſwer required fromthe above ſaid El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, upon the <hi>5th</hi> of <hi>Iune 1653.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="answer">
                  <head>Querie 1. <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether you have the Eternal Spirit which gave forth the Scriptures, yea or no?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Anſw. We do believe and aſſert, that all <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwelling of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the Saints.</note> that do believe in Jeſus Chriſt (of which number we take our ſelves to be) have the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rom. 8. 9,</hi> dwelling in them, 1 <hi>Cor. 3. 16.</hi> Which Spirit is God, <hi>Acts 10. 3. 5.</hi> compared with verſ. 19, 20. and therefore Eternal; <hi>Dout. 33. 27.</hi> and he who gave forth the Scriptures, 2 <hi>Pet. 1. 21. 2 Tim. 3. 16.</hi> But we do not believe that there is any ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, eſſential or perſonal union, betwixt this Eternal Spirit and ſuch Believers; For ſuch Unions would either make the Spirit and Believers ſome third thing, as when ſoul and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:166753:10"/> are united, a third thing which is neither ſoul nor body, but compounded of both, ariſeth from it, which is called Man; or elſe thee will be a confounding of ſubſtance which cannot be; for God cannot mix with the Creature. And elſe ſuch Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on if it ſhould be Perſonal, as betwixt the two Natures in Chriſt, would make Believers God, and equal with Chriſt, and conſequently equal with God himſelf; The Conſequence of which would be, thatſuch Perſons would have an Almighty Power, which they might put forth in working as many mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles as they pleaſe, as they may ſee it make for the Glory of God, and that they would be omniſcient and know all things, and would have the reſt of Gods Atributes as Chriſt had, who was God andequal with God, and in whom this Perſonal Union was; But this is palpsbly falſe in reference to Saints, and is full of Blaſphemy.</p>
                  <p>And though we believe that the Spirit of Chriſt dwels in Saints, yet we aſſert the Spirit of Chriſt to be diſtinct from the Saint, and the Saints from the Spirit, And though he dwells in the Saints, yet he acts not in them but as it pleaſeth him; neither doth he impart Wiſdom, Power, Grace and Glory but as it pleaſeth him; 1 <hi>Cor. 12. 7.</hi> to 12. And though there be the ſame Spirit in all Saints that gave ſorth the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, yet all Saints have not the ſame Inſpiration of the Spirit which the Prophets and Apoſtles had, ſo as they ſhould be able to give forth infallible Truths, and immediatly diſcover the pure and clear will of God as the Prophets and Apoſtles did; <hi>Timothy</hi> had the Spirit of God, yet he muſt give attendance to Reading, 1 <hi>Tim. 1. 13.</hi> and 2 <hi>Tim. 1. 14. 15.</hi> He muſt continue in the things he had learned and had been aſſured of, knowing of whom he had learned them. And the holy Scriptures which of a child he had the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of, are thoſe Writings to which the Apoſtle ſends him as being able to make him wiſe to Salvation. The Spirit within him did not dictate all things to him, but he muſt have recourſe to the Scriptures. God dwelt in the Temple, but God did not make out all his Glory in the Temple. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times there was no Glory at all that was viſible, and yet God was there; and when there was Glory, there was not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:166753:10"/> all that might have been: And Believers are the Temple of the Holy Ghoſt, and the Spirit of God dwels in them; but God doth not make out all his glory in them, not all the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry his Wiſdom, Power, Holineſs, or of the reſt of his Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes; For neither is there a capacity in the Crreature to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, neither doth the Spirit communicate according to the capacity, but it is reſerved for another time and place; and now every Saint is in weakneſs and infirmity, as in Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſo in all other Graces. <hi>1 Cor. 13. 9.</hi> to 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="answer">
                  <head>Querie 2. <hi>Whether the Apoſtles did give a right meaning</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſenſe of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</note> 
                     <hi>to the Scriptures when they gave them forth, or left them to you to give the meaning of them, yea or no?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Apoſtles and ſo all the Penmen of Scriptures, in all the Scriptures they gave forth, had a meaning, and they gave it forth in and with thoſe Scriptures which they gave forth, yet not alwayes ſo plainly that the meaning thereof might be rightly taken up by thoſe that read them, unleſs compared with ſome other Scriptures which they alſo have given out, which have a plainer ſenſe in them, and are help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to expound them; 1 <hi>Cor. 2. 13.</hi> Chriſt ſaith unto the <hi>Jews who required a Sign? Ioh. 2. 19. Deſtroy this Temple and in three daies I will raiſe it up again:</hi> Chriſt had a ſenſe in which he meant thoſe words; he underſtood what himſelf ſaid; but the <hi>Iews</hi> underſtood it not, could not take up the ſenſe, but applyed the words to a Material Building; But the Evangeliſt gives the right ſenſe, in which Chriſt intended them; and we come to know the right ſenſe, not by the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the words themſelves; for more things are ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified then one by one word, as the word (Temple) ſignifieth plainly and properly a material houſe where God gave his Preſence and was worſhipped; but ſiguratively and myſtically the Body of man in which the Soul dwels. In this metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical ſenſe Chriſt meant it; But this did not appear to them, nor would it have appeared to us by the ſignification of the word, if in another place of Scripture the Evangeliſt had not given the interpretation; <hi>Ioh. 2. 21, 22.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> tels us, 2 <hi>Pet. 3. 16.</hi> that ſome things in Paul Epiſtles were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166753:11"/> hard to be underſtood, which they which were unlearned and unſtable did wreſt to their own deſtruction. There was a ſenſe which <hi>Paul</hi> gave forth in thoſe Seriptures in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, but it was not eaſie but hard to be underſtood, and ſo hard that they who were unlearned in the Scriptures, not well read therein, not well verſ'd, not well acquainted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, did wreſt them; and unſtable ones by reaſon of the difficulty that was in the ſenſe of them, did pervert them to their own and others ruin. Chriſt in his Parables that he gave out (which are part of Scripture) had a meaning, But the meaning was ſo myſtical and hidden, that the Diſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples could not have found it out, if Chriſt himſelf in other words had not given the ſenſe and meaning thereof. And <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> &amp; the Prophets wrote of Chriſt ſo darkly &amp; obſcurely, that though themſelves knew what they meant in what they wrote, <hi>Iohn 12. 41,</hi> yet others did not; the Diſciples did not till Chriſt firſt expounded unto them the things which <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets wrote of him: <hi>Luk 24. 26, 27.</hi> Therefore it is that Chriſt commmands <hi>to ſearch the Scriptures,</hi> becauſe the meaning lieth deep in many places, and is hidden from the common eye; yet by ſearching what Scriptures layd together ſpeak, the ſenſe may be gotten out.</p>
                  <p>In Anſwer therefore to the Queſtion, the Apoſtles when they gave out the Scriptures, they gave out the ſenſe in ſome places more darkly, in other places more clearly; ſo that the ſenſe and meaning may be taken up (at leaſt in all the, great Points of Faith) if Scriptures be compared with each other; And they have not left them to us, nor to any others to give the ſenſe of them, that is, to put any ſenſe of our own upon ſuch Scriptures which they have given out, which is not their ſenſe: but that which is Jeft to us, is, to find out the ſenſe and meaneing which they have put, as in <hi>Re2. 13. 18.</hi> after ſome myſtical things had been held out in which there was a mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but hard to be underſtood, it is is ſaid, <hi>Here is Wiſdom; let him that underſtandeth count the Number of the Beaſt;</hi> that is, let him ſet all his Wiſdom and underſtanding that he hath on work to ſearch it out. Nevertheleſs it is not to be underſtood, that the meaning which the Apoſtles intended
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:166753:11"/> in the Scripture which they gave out, doth perpetually fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the ſound of the Letter; for the Letter contains con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction many times in it, but the Apoſtles meaning as he interprets himſelf, hath ſweet congruity in it without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="answer">
                  <head>Querie 3. <hi>Whether Plagues be not added to them who add</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing from the Scripture, In what ſenſe it is to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood.</note> 
                     <hi>to the Prophecies Written in the Book? And whether his name be not diminiſhed out of the Book of Life who diminiſheth? And whether you can witneſs this name, yea or no?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is plain and clear from <hi>Rev. 22. 18.</hi> that the Evils are great and terrible, that are threatned againſt adding and diminiſhing; But what this adding and diminiſhing is that hath ſuch woes belonging to it, is the queſtion; If ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the Scripture, and interpreting it, and ſhewing the ſenſe and meaning thereof, be the adding or diminiſhing that the queſtion intends, againſt which ſuch a fearful Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is pronounced, then it would reach <hi>Ezra</hi> and thoſe others with him mentioned. <hi>Nehem. 8. 7, 8.</hi> For they read and they gave the ſenſe, and cauſed the people to underſtand the reading. And Chriſt alſo gave the ſenſe of thoſe words in <hi>Iſai. 61. 1, 2, 3.</hi> and declared how they were fulfilled in himſelf; and he expounded <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, their Writings to thoſe two Diſciples who were travelling towards <hi>Emmaus.</hi> And <hi>Philip</hi> guided the <hi>Eunuch</hi> in his reading unto the right ſenſe of the Prophet <hi>Iſar.</hi> in Chap. 53. 7, 8, 9. He ſhewed the Prophet ſpake not of himſelf but of another, <hi>via.</hi> Chriſt; <hi>Acts 8. 31. 34</hi> And what was preaching the Goſpal ordained of God for? And why were Gifts given unto men? but that the People might be brought to Knowledge, and might come to underſtand the Scriptures. Therefore the Apoſtles were much exerciſed in opening thoſe ſealed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies which were often read and never underſtood, which reſpected Chriſt, and in proving out of them that Jeſus was the Chriſt. Therefore the interpreting of Scripture is not adding to it, ſo long as it is not any private interpretation that is given, which a mans heart hath found out and his
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166753:12"/> fancy hath imagined; but ſuch an interpretation as agreeth to the Spirit of the Scripture in other places. 2 <hi>Pet. 1. 20, 21.</hi> and ſuch as accords with the Analogy of Faith. <hi>Rom. 12. 6.</hi> that is, holds Proportion with the Doctrine of Faith as it is laid down in other Scriptures; This is not adding; but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is, when the ſufficiency of the Scriptures to build men up to ſalvation, and to make them perfect, throughly furniſhed unto every good work, is not acknowledged; and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Traditions, Canons, and Doctrines and Commandments of men are brought in and annexed and impoſed upon the people; As of old, by the Scribes and Phariſees which Chriſt ſo often conflicted with; and by the Roman Synagogue, and by ſome of that ſtamp amongſt our ſelves; And when Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons aſſume an Authority and Power to themſelves to be the Judges of the Scripture, and expunge what they pleaſe out of it, and introduce into it what liketh them, and what ſenſe they give unto it, whether it agrees or not agres with other Scriptures, yet that muſt be the ſenſe of of it, and none muſt queſtion it: Whereas Scripture it ſelf ought to be its own interpreter, elſe there would be no plain ſtanding rule to try truth by, but the Truth of God muſt be ſubjected to the various and oppoſite fancies of men. And when Perſons pretend the Spirit, and ſay they have dreamed, and come with their apprehenſions, and ſay it is made out ſo to them or it is ſo given in to them; and though there be never ſo much repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy in it to other Scriptures, yet that muſt be the ſenſe; by which means the Spirit of Truth comes to ſuffer many affronts in this Age; This is adding: And (indeed) the rigid adhering to the letter of Scriptures and to the ſound of words therein, without admitting a wholeſom ſenſe, ſuch as accords with other Scriptures, is adding, which is the way of all Seducers and Deceivers to make their blaſphemous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine the more vendible. For the letter of Scripture in ſome places, without ſearching out a ſound ſenſe, will coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance Papiſts, Arrians, Ranters, and whom not ! in their Tenents; This is the introducing of another Scripture then that which is Scripture indeed; and it is properly ſuch adding to the Scripture, againſt which ſuch plagues are denounced.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166753:12"/> Let theſe Perſons who are called Quakers, look to this, for it is their grand impoſture wherewith they beguilc the people; they bring the Letter where it ſerves for their purpoſe, as the Papiſts were wont to bring their <hi>hoc eſt corpus meum,</hi> This is my Body, to prove the bodily preſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament. And theſe preſs upon the people the Letter, and cry out upon the Miniſters of Chriſt and ſay, they are lying Prieſts, and they lead the people in darkneſs, and ſo by the Letter deſtroy the ſenſe of Scripture, and bring in another ſenſe which is not Scripture-ſenſe, and ſo themſelves are found both adders to and diminiſhers from the Scripture.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="answer">
                  <head>Querie 4. <hi>Whether you have an infallible Judgement to judge of things eternal, yea or no?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Infali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility in judging how fat men may have it, and how far not.</note>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The firſt ſtate of every man is darkneſs; <hi>the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral man underſtands not the things that are of God, they are fooliſhneſs unto him, neither can he know them, becauſe they are spiritually diſcerned.</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 14. When any man is brought from darkneſs to light, even then he knoweth but in part; <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf was in ſome darkneſs; <hi>now we ſee through a glaſs darkly,</hi> ſaid he of himſelf and others, 1 <hi>Cor. 13. 12.</hi> Thoſe to whom <hi>John</hi> wrote, who had the annointment to teach them all things, and of whom <hi>John</hi> ſaid that they knew all things, (which was but an hyperbolical expreſſion, and did import only much knowledge to be in them; 1 <hi>Ioh. 2. 20, 21, 27.)</hi> yet thoſe were not all light without any darkneſs, but they were ſuch who might be deceived, and were ſubject to errour; therefore the Apoſtle warns them of Seducers, not withſtanding the unction that they have received. They had not an infallible judgement, but might be miſtaken in ſome of the things of God, though they had the Spirit; for the Spirit gives himſelf out to thoſe in whom he is, in light, in power and grace as he will. Therefore neither we nor any others have infallible judgments in all things at all times, but we are ſubject to Errour, and in many things we do not apprehend and ſpeak aright of God, of Chriſt, of the Spirit, of the Saints, of our ſelves, of the myſteries of the Goſpel,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166753:13"/> which are ſome of thoſe things which are eternal; As God ſaid to <hi>Iobs</hi> Friends, <hi>Ye have not ſpoken of me the things that are right, as my Servant</hi> Job <hi>hath;</hi> and <hi>Iob</hi> himſelf did dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Counſel by words without knowledge, when he ſpake of God.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding that fallible mind and judgement that is in all men in ſome things, and at ſome times; yet becauſe the Rule that is left men to judge by, is an infallible, ſure and certain Rule, which cannot deceive men, and becauſe it is a plain Rule in many things and eaſily underſtood, <hi>Prov. 1. 4.</hi> and becauſe the principles of Religion and fundamentals of Salvation are ſo clearly revealed in the Scripture, that Babes in Chriſt may come to the knowledge of them; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both we and all the Saints, may in ſome things have an infallible judgement, and may judge of things eternal with a judgement of Certainty, both reſpecting God, Chriſt, Faith, Repentance, Reſurrection of the dead, eternal judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and many other things. How elſe could there be any preaching, if perſons could not know infallibly, that in ſome things they hold forth they ſpeak the Truth; And how could any thing be aſſuredly believed, if the word of Faith in the true ſenſe of it, could not infallibly be held forth, and judged of? And how could any Perſon be at a certainty concerning his own Salvation? And how could any Chriſtian ſeal the Truth of Chriſt with his blood, if ſome things could not be judged of with an infallible judgement?</p>
                  <p>But whether any perſon having not the Spirit, can have an infallible judgement to judge of things eternal, by the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge they may get from the Scripture, is the drift and ſcope of the queſtion, if I be able to make a judgement of it. They think that none can infallibly judge of things of an eternal nature, but ſuch who have the Spirit; and that we are perſons that have not the Spirit, and therefore cannot judge of them nor of their way, and that they themſelves have the Spirit, and that judgement belongs to them only, both of perſons and of things; we are but in our firſt birth, and are carnal, and know not things of an eternal Nature; they are in the ſecond birth, and are ſpiritual, and can judge all things;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166753:13"/> and all men, for hitherto tends a great part of a large Letter ſent unto us from them, by which I come to prove them in this queſtion. In anſwer therefore unto this, I muſt diſtinguiſh of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible judgement: There is an infallible Judgment which may be made from the Scripture without the Spirit, and there's an infallible judgment which cannot be made from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture without the ſpirit. The Judgment that may be made from the Scripture without the Spirit infallibly, reſpects the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which the Scripture contains to be received &amp; believed by men that they may be ſaved; what they be, and what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of life it is, that Perſons ought to live that would come to Life eternal; theſe things are clearly and plainly laid down, and may eaſily be taken up by unprejudiced Perſons, who have unballanced ſpirits, though they have not the ſpirit. Upon this account it is that the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> would not have every Spirit believed, but would have the ſpirits tryed whether they be of God; but how muſt they be tried unleſs by the Scriptures? for every one will pretend the Spirit, and there are many falſe Prophets who have the ſpirit of deluſion, and are gone forth into the world; <hi>1 Joh. 4. 1.</hi> For if the Scripture were not the judge of the Spirit in this caſe, ſo far as concerns Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Manners which men have Received and learned, whether they be of God or no; or whether the ſpirit of the Devil hath not inſpiried them: therewith, all men living would be put upon deſperate uncertainties, which is the Spirit that gives our the Truth, and which is the ſpirit of Errour. And they would be confounded through the multiplicity of ſpirits, each ſpirit pretending to Truth, and crying down the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary as Errour; Therefore the Scripture alone being of the Spirits inſpiring, is a light ſufficient to ſhew the Doctrine what it is, and the commandment &amp; precept what it is, to one that will attend unto it, without any further inſpiration of the Spirit; elſe in vain were the Scriptures at the firſt inſpired.</p>
                  <p>But then again there is an infallible Judgement which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be made without the Spirit, that is, whether thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and Rules of Life which are clearly contained in the Scripture be Doctrines which proceeded from God? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God ſpake with <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſent Chriſt to declare what he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166753:14"/> hath declared, inſpired the Apoſtles in ſpeaking and writing what they have ſpoken or written, or whether all theſe ſpake of themſelves. It is the Spirit of God alone that can give aſſured ſatisfaction concerning this. The Jews and their Rulers, though they ſaw the Miracles, yet they know not Chriſt to be the Meſſiah; for had they known him, they would never have crucified the Lord of glory. Theſe are among thoſe inviſible things which are revealed unto us by the Spirit, as the Apoſtle tels us, <hi>1 Cor. 2. 8, 9, 10.</hi> It is eaſie for any man that hath his reaſon, and hath not the Spirit, by read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scripture to conclude that Scripture makes Jeſus the Son of <hi>Mary</hi> to be the Son of God, and the Chriſt; But for any man to beleeve it, and build upon it as a ſure truth of God, this is from the Spirit; fleſh and blood hath not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed this, but the Father which is in Heaven; Chriſt told <hi>Peter</hi> ſo, <hi>Mat. 16 16.</hi> The concluſion is, That the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the foundation of an inſallible judgement concerning things contained in them, and not the Spirit: but both Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Spirit muſt concur to give in the certainty of thoſe things that are there contained, that they may become a ſure rock to be built upon; for no one can ſay aſſuredly, and by a ſpirit of Faith, that Jeſus is the Lord, but by the holy Ghoſt, <hi>1 Cor. 12. 3.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="answer">
                  <head>Quere 5. <hi>Whether you be above the Apoſtle, and able to</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, what may be granted and what not.</note> 
                     <hi>judge his condition, becauſe you ſay he was not perfect who ſaid he ſpake wiſedom among them that were perfect?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Queſtion relates to a paſſage in our Anſwer to a Letter of theirs which pleaded for perfection; (which we had the ſight of) which fell into their hands, and hath oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned this Queſtion. The words of our Anſwer are theſe, <hi>He might have diſcerned that Paul expreſsly denies perfection in reference to himſelf, Phil. 3. 12.</hi> His Queſtion hence is, <hi>Are you above the Apoſtle, and able to judge his condition, becauſe you ſay he was not perfect?</hi> It is a ſenceleſs, fooliſh, cauſeleſs Queſtion, becauſe he judged nothing of the Apoſtles condition, but perverted what the Apoſtle judged of his own condition; for it is his own words of himſelf, which are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:166753:14"/> ſpoken in the above mentioned place, not our words of him. <hi>Not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as though I had already apprehended or were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready perfect.</hi> We relate his words, And do we exalt our ſelves in it above him, and judge his condition? As for his ſpeaking of Wiſedom among thoſe who were perfect, that proves not his perfection of which the Queſtion runs, nor (indeed) doth it prove any perfection at all, which excludes all ſin, which is that which they drive at in making mention of it. There is a comparative perfection which ſome attain unto, which the Apoſtle intends in that place: There are ſome that are in their way towards it, and have made a good progreſs, and are ſtill paſſing thitherward; theſe are perfect in compariſon of the rude wild world, and of ſuch who are onely babes in Chriſt: He that can bridle his tongue, is a perfect man, as <hi>James</hi> affirms, not abſolutely perfect; for the heart may be unruly, though the tongue be reſtrained; but comparatively perfect, becauſe there are not many who can do it; amongſt ſuch perfect ones <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks wiſdom, but not amongſt abſolute Perfectiſts.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="answer">
                  <head>Querie 6. <hi>Whether you have the hidden wiſdom which God</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſt in Saints, in what ſenſe they have him, and in what ſenſe not.</note> 
                     <hi>ordained before the World was, which the Apoſtle speaks of, yea or no?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> This hidden Wiſdom which God, ordained before the world was, which the Apoſtle ſpeaks of in <hi>1 Cor.</hi> 2. 7. is CHRIST; for he is called the Wiſdom of God, <hi>1 Cor. 1. 24.</hi> and he is hidden alſo; for he was in the World, and the World knew him not, and he came unto his own, and his own re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him not, <hi>Joh. 1. 11. 12.</hi> For though they ſaid they knew him, and whence he was, yet Chriſt told them, That they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knew him nor his Father, nor whence he was, nor whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he went; For though they knew him as he was man, yet the Divinity which was vailed in his fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſh, they ſaw no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could ſee; for fleſh and blood revealed it not, but the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as Chriſt told his Diſciples; and it is clear from the above-mentioned place, which he alludes to in this Queſtion, that Chriſt is the perſon that is called <hi>The hidden wiſdom which</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:166753:15"/> 
                     <hi>God erdained;</hi> For the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>verſ. 8. Had they known it, they would never have crucified the Lord of glory:</hi> Now if Chriſt be this hidden Wiſdom, then the Queſtion runs of Chriſt, whether we have him, yea or no? Our Anſwer to it is this: What we are will appear in time; but if we be Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, we have him; for all Believers have him; <hi>for he dwells in their hearts by faith,</hi> Eph. 3. 17. <hi>For faith receives him,</hi> Joh. 1. 12. And who ever hath one of the three, hath all the three dwelling in him. If Saints have the holy Ghoſt (as was grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the firſt Queſtion,) Then they have Chriſt alſo; nay, they could not have the Spirit, if they had not Chriſt; for Chriſt ſends him; yet it muſt be underſtood in a ſpiritual ſenſe that they have Chriſt, and not in a literal and carnal. They have Chriſt ſtanding in relation to them and they to him, as the members have the head becauſe they are united to it and it to them, and as branches have the Vine, and the Vine the branches, becauſe united to one another. And they have Chriſts influence upon them, and Chriſt in thoſe influences: And they have the vertue and power of his Spirit put forth in them in ſuch meaſure as pleaſeth him, but always in part, and not in perfection, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 12. and therein they have him. But they have not Chriſt in fleſh, or the fleſh of Chriſt dwelling in them; for that was taken up into Heaven and will be there contained, till the reſtitution of all things. But they intend this Queſtion of an higher way of having Chriſt, and they dream that they themſelves have him in a higher way, and that neither we nor any others but themſelves have him in that way. They imagine ſuch an having of Chriſt as the fleſh of Chriſt had God, or as the humanity of Chriſt had the Godhead: The fleſh of Chriſt had God in ſuch ſort, that it was wholy comprehended of God, and taken up into oneneſs of Perſon with him, ſo as that the infinite power and wiſdom and holineſs of God, was put forth many times in fleſh; and always when the fleſh (that is, when the humanity) acted any thing, it was in perfection of compliance with God, which was in it and comprehended it; Such an having of Chriſt as this, they conceit in reference to themſelves, that as the Godhead had the fleſh, ſo they have the Godhead, which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166753:15"/> ſupplies with all Wiſdom, Knowledge, Graces of all kindes, ſtrength, holineſs, and with every thing, ſo that they neede nothing that is external, neither Scripture, nor Ordinances, or Teachers, but Chriſt whom they have within them is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent for all things, and unto all purpoſes, and makes them perfect as Chriſt is, as God is; Now ſuch an having of Chriſt as this is, we aſſume not nor dare aſſume; And we declare againſt it as a Satanical deluſion, to which God hath left theſe poor Creatures, who have forſaken him. They would be as God, as Chriſt; the Devil tempts them to it, as at firſt he did our firſt Parents, tells them that they are ſo, and ſo they caſt off his Inſtitutions, Ordinances, Servants, which he ſends in his name, and him in them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="answer">
                  <head>Querie 7. <hi>Whether you have heard the voice of the live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate voyces, whether there be any ſuch immediate voyces now as of old time to the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. Or, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning immediate inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                     <hi>God of Heaven and Earth? or whether you do not take the Prophets words, Chriſts words, and the Apoſtles words, and ſay, he ſaith it, when ſaith the Lord, I never ſpoke to you?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> This Queſtion conſiſts of two parts; The former part demands of us, Whether we be perſons immediately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired in what we deliver. For the voyce which they en quire after, is ſome voyce that immediately comes from God, ſuch as came to the Patriarks, to <hi>Moſes,</hi> to <hi>Samuel,</hi> to all the Prophets, to Chriſt and to all the Apoſtles, The Jews would confeſs that God ſpake with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and we Chriſtians will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that God ſpake both with <hi>Moſes</hi> and with Chriſt; for all Scripture was given by Inſpiration of God, and holy men of old ſpake as they were inſpired by the holy Ghoſt. And this we aſſert in reference to the New Teſtament as well as in reference to the old, becauſe God by ſigns and wonders and with divers Miracles hath given Witneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. Now our Anſwer is, That ſuch a voyce as this, as comes immediately from God, we have not heard, and ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration as this we have not received, nor do we wait for it; And if the perſons who propound this Queſtion, have heard any ſuch immediate voyce as this (for they pretend much to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:166753:16"/> it, and ſay Gods ſpeaks unto them, and the Spirit immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuggeſts what they ſpeak or pray in their meetings, coming unto them at ſuch time as they quake and tremble; and their quaking is the ſign by which others know that the Spirit is come unto them) let ſuch perſons confirm Gods ſpeaking or the Spirits ſpeaking to them by ſigns and wonders and by d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie of Miracles as Chriſt and his Apoſtles did, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 3, 4. elſe they muſt of neceſſity be acounted Impoſtors and Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of the People.</p>
                  <p>The latter part of the Queſtion ſhews the evilneſs of their deſign, and what it is that they ſtrike at; it is at preaching out of the Scriptures; they would have no preaching but what immediately proceeds from the ſuggeſtion of the Spirit, which they pretend to have; and herein lies the venome and poyſon of the Queſtion, as they are the propounders of it; And they would make all preachers, ſave ſuch who preach by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate dictate of the Spirit as the Prophets did and the Apoſtles did, to be falſe Prophets and Teachers of lyes, which cell the people that the Lord hath ſaid ſo, and the Lord never ſpake to them; Let this be looked into and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, It will be granted by themſelves, that God ſpake by <hi>Moſes.</hi> by the Prophets, by Chriſt, and by the Apoſtles, and that all their words are Gods Words; and what ever they ſaid in their Propheſies, and preachings, or Epiſtles, that they wrote, God ſaid it by them; this is clear from <hi>Heb. 1. 1, 2. God ſpake in times paſt unto our Fathers by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, It muſt be granted without contradiction, that what ever the Fathers heard of God at any time during the Old Teſtament, it was taken out of the Prophets, it was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that God ſpake by the Prophets; For the Prieſts and the Levites, which were the Inſtructers of the Fathers and Teachers of the people, ſpake not any thing which they had received immediately from God by voyce, but what God had ſpoken by the Prophets, or by <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was alſo a Prophet; We ſhall finde that <hi>Ezra</hi> a Prieſt and the Levices with him, read in the Law, and gave the ſenſe, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 7. 8.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166753:16"/> Now the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> compriſeth all the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Jewes of the Old Teſtament had through all Generations whilſt that Teſtament was ſtanding, under this head, Gods teaching them by the Prophets. Now we know there were not Prophets at all times in all Generations, who brought immediate Meſſages from God; The laſt of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets was <hi>Malachy,</hi> and there were many Ages after that, yet the people were taught all along by the Prophets; for the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>God ſpake to our Fathers by the Prophets:</hi> But how could that be when the Prophets were dead? Yea; for though the Prophets were dead, yet their Propheſies were li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and remaining, and were made uſe of by the Miniſters of the Old Teſtament, and urged and preſſed upon the people as the Word of the Lord: And Chriſt is ſaid to have ſpoken unto us, when onely the words of Chriſt are brought unto us, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 25. And what ever it be that the Prophets or Chriſt have ſpoken from the Lord while upon the Earth, when ſuch words are urged upon a people, it muſt be accounted God preſent ſpeaking. The Apoſtles dehortation is, <hi>Heb. 12. 25. Not to refuſe him that ſpeaketh,</hi> he ſpeaks in the preſent Tenſe, though Chriſt was then in Heaven, and ſpake not; but what he hath ſpoken, when it is preſented, muſt be accounted his preſent ſpeaking. Chriſt himſelf expounded unto the Diſciples The words that <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophers had ſpoken reſpecting his ſufferings, and preſſeth them upon their Faith, as words ſpoken by God, blaming them for their unbelief; And <hi>Paul</hi> applyed the words that God ſpake by <hi>Eſay</hi> the Prophet, to theſe unbelieving Jews that withſtood his preaching as Gods Meſſage to them, and ſaid they were <hi>The words of the Holy Ghoſt. Act.</hi> 28, 25. 26. And his whole wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that he gave of Chriſt, was fetched out of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets. <hi>Act.</hi> 26. 2. And all that are brought to the Faith of Chriſt, are ſaid to be built upon the Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 20. Not upon an immediate voyce that comes from God to themſelves or to any others who are their Teachers, but upon the Word of God that was of old ſpoken by the Prophets; and this is called a more ſure word then any immediate word, unleſs it come notably, marvellouſly, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166753:17"/> viſibly confirmed unto them. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19. For there may be much fallacy in that, and much deluſion; but we know that God ſpake with <hi>Moſes,</hi> and with the Prophets; ſo alſo with Chriſt and with the Apoſtles; and what was ſpoken to them, was intended to continue as a rule till Chriſts appearing, <hi>Iſai. 8. 20. 1 Tim 6. 13, 14.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, It is evident from Scripture, that what ever the Prophets or Apoſtles have ſpoken or written, is to be ſafely kept and retained, and alſo transferred and made over to others, and theſe others are to communicate and make the ſame known to others after them, and ſo it is to paſs from man to man, and from age to age, and never to be loſt, but kept as a precious treaſury is kept for the benefit of after Poſterity. And conſequently that God did not intend im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate teaching, nor to give out an immediate voyce in after ages, which ſhould direct and guide men in the wayes of Salvation, 2 <hi>Tim. 2. 2. The things that thou haſt heard from me among many witneſſes, the ſame commit thou to faithful men who ſhall be able to teach others alſo.</hi> This is the way in which God intended the propagating of the knowledge of himſelf, and of his Son, and of his will. <hi>Paul</hi> muſt have his knowledge immediately, but not <hi>Timothy,</hi> but he muſt have it from <hi>Paul,</hi> and thoſe faithful men from him, and others from them; ſo the truth of God muſt paſs from hand to hand throughout all Generations. And the Faith, <hi>viz.</hi> the Doctrine of Faith is ſaid to be once delivered to the Saints, <hi>Jude</hi> 3. and that very Doctrine which was once delivered, muſt be always contended for: This <hi>(once)</hi> imports as much as <hi>already, as verſ.</hi> 5. ſhewes, or <hi>(once delivered)</hi> is once for all, never more to be delivered. It hath been delivered, that is, immediately from Heaven, and that cuts off all expectations of any other delivery from Heaven, and of all other imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate voyces thence; But all Saints muſt hold what they have once had, 2 <hi>Theſ. 2. 15. Hold the Traditions</hi> (ſaid <hi>Paul) which ye have been taught whether by word or by our Epiſtle.</hi> Every Biſhop or Elder (for they are one in Scripture expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) muſt hold faſt the faithful word, as he hath been taught, that he may be able by ſound Doctrine, both to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:166753:17"/> and convince gain-ſayers, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 9, 10. And the reaſon is rendred, becauſe <hi>there are many unruly and vain talkers and deceivers, whoſe mouthes muſt be ſtopped, who ſubvert whole houſes,</hi> verſ. 10. 11. There muſt not be waiting for a new word, an immediate word, but that word which hath been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready taught, muſt be held faſt; and that is the ſound Doctrine which muſt be made uſe of to convince and exhort men by; and this word may be called the Word of the Lord to the Apoſtles and Prophets, for our uſe and benefit, though not ſpoken to us immediately, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Well ſpake the holy Ghoſt by Iſaiah;</hi> he did not ſay, <hi>Well ſpake the holy Ghoſt to me,</hi> but to <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> It was Gods Word to <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> which he made uſe of againſt that people to whom he ſpake, though not Gods word to him immediately.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="answer">
                  <head>Querie 8. <hi>Whether a man ſhall overcome the body of ſin</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſin, what free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have from it, and what not.</note> 
                     <hi>while he is upon the Earth, yea or no?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> If this Queſtion be meant of a full and perfect Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory over the body of ſin, which is accompanied with the utter deſtruction of the body of ſin, ſo as that there ſhall be no remainders of it abiding in men, ſo as that perſons ſhall be all Spirit, and no fleſh, and in a perfect ſtate without any propenſity to ſin; then the Anſwer muſt be negative; no man while upon Earth, ſhall overcome the body of ſin after ſuch manner: For the Apoſtle declares the condition of all the Saints in this World, <hi>Gal. 5. 17. The fleſh luſteth againſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit againſt the fleſh; and theſe are contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the one to the other, ſo that ye cannot do the things that ye would;</hi> and the ſame Apoſtle in <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 14. to the end, deſcribes in his own perſon the vexatious exerciſe that all Believers have more or leſs in this World, through contrary laws within them, <hi>viz.</hi> through the law of the fleſh, and the law of the minde, which are always warring one againſt the other. And though they do delight in the Law of God after the inward man, yet many times through the ſtrength of ſin within them, they know not how to perform that which is good: And this made the Apoſtle groan for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166753:18"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:166753:18"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:166753:19"/> 
                     <hi>v. 24. Oh wretched man that I am, who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me, &amp;c.</hi> And though he <hi>thanks God through Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> yet it was not for any perfect or full deliverance that he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained after his groaning from this condition; for he concludes of himſelf in the very next words after his thankſgiving, <hi>That with the minde he himſelf ſerved the Law of God, but with the fleſh the law of ſin.</hi> And the deliverance which he had in Chriſt, was from the Curſe of ſuch a ſtate, rather then from the ſtate it ſelf; and from ſuch dominion as would make him a perfect Captive, from which he was kept; For ſtill his will was to do good, though many times, the good which he would have done he did it not. And it was deliverance he apprehended by Faith would be through Jeſus Chriſt to him at laſt, in which he rejoyced, and for which he thanked God, rather then for any victorious ſtrength he at that time poſſeſſed. And he ſaw it in Chriſt the head already, and aſſured himſelf of it in due time upon that account. But an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming of the body of ſin, ſuch as delivers from all ſin in this world, is expreſly againſt the Scripture, as hath been already declared in our Letter which we ſent in Anſwer to that pleaded-for perfection contained in a Letter of theirs brought to our view. But if the Queſtion reſpect onely a partial overcoming, and ſuch as is imperfect, and is onely in tendency towards perfection of conqueſt, it will then be condeſcended to; For Saints go forth conquering and to conquer, and yet ſometimes have the worſt of it, and are as Captives, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 23. And yet are never totally diſarmed, but reaſſume the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of their warfare, and take hold on Gods ſtrengh, and get the better again, and weaken the fleſhly part by a power from on high. And in ſuch a ſenſe as this, it will be granted, that a man may and doth overcom the body of ſin. He is about the work and is doing it; by the power of the Spirit, he is mortifying the deeds of the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 13. and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that through Chriſt ſtrengthening him, he ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly Conqueror at the laſt, he may be ſaid to have done it, as in 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. 4.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="answer">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:166753:19"/>
                  <head>Querie 9. <hi>Whether you preach no other Doctrine but</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preach<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeeing of Chriſt with our bodily eys, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him with our bodily ears, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of him with our bodily hands, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles did, yea or no?</note> 
                     <hi>what the Apoſtles did? That which was from the beginning, which we have heard, which we have ſeen with our eyes, which we have looked upon, and our hands have handled of the word of life. For this life is made manifeſt, and we have ſeen it, and bear witneſs and ſhew it unto you.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi> This Queſtion is propoſed upon occaſion of <hi>John's</hi> Preface to his firſt Epiſtle, where <hi>John</hi> firſt declares the ſubject which he would bear witneſs of, and that was Chriſt, ſaid to be from the beginning in reference to his Diety, and ſaid to be one heard, ſeen, handled, in reference to his huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; And afterwards he declares his aſſurance which he had in witneſſing and ſhewing what he ſhould preſent; he would ſhew them nothing but what he had both heard, ſeen, and handled, and therefore could confirm the truth thereof unto them; Now the Queſtion demands of us, whether we preach no other Doctrine, then ſuch as <hi>John</hi> preached? Is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, Whether we preach Chriſt as he did? if ſo, we could reſolve him, that we aym at no other thing but to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt Chriſt. And we would have all our preaching tend thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But there is another thing intended in the Queſtion, Whether we preach with that aſſurance that he did, nothing but what we have heard of him, and ſeen of him, and handled and felt of him, and what is after this manner manifeſt unto us and within us. And if this be the ſenſe (as without doubt it is) then the Anſwer muſt be that we do not preach that Chriſt whom we have ſeen with out bodily eys, heard with our bodily ears, and handled with out bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly hands; for Chriſt is in Heaven in his humanity, and not on Earth; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to be ſeen, heard, or handled by us or any other that live on Earth; But that Chriſt which <hi>John</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles heard, ſaw, and handled, we preach, and we do not give our own aſſurance, but the Apoſtles aſſurance; and we conceive that the Apoſtles aſſurance is as good now as it was then; And we have warrant to preach what we have underſtood from their writings, though we have not ſeen
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:166753:20"/> with our eyes; even as <hi>Timothy</hi> was commanded to preach and ſhew what he had heard of the Apoſtle, who yet himſelf had not heard, nor ſeen, nor handled any thing of Chriſt; and he muſt commit them to faithful men, who had ſeen no more then he, and they muſt teach others alſo; But this Queſtion holds affinity with the ſeventh Queſtion, to which I refer the Reader; onely I ſhall add this, that if the perſons that make theſe propoſals do glory over us, becauſe we have not thus ſeen Chriſt, and do give it out that he hath appeared to them, and that they have ſeen him, and heard him, and heard him, and that he is with and in them; let them ſeriouſly conſider, whether it be the true Chriſt, the ſame whom <hi>Iohn</hi> heard or ſaw with his bodily eyes, and handled with his bodily hands, which they have ſeen, or a bodileſs Chriſt of their own framing. And whether their ſeeing of Chriſt be not like <hi>Saul</hi> his ſeeing <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> who indeed ſaw the Devil in <hi>Samuels</hi> ſhape, and talked with him, and had fellowſhip with him, but ſaw not <hi>Samuel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="answer">
                  <head>Querie 10. <hi>Whether you have this word which was from</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt what it is; And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning preaching from the letter how far it may and muſt be, and how far not.</note> 
                     <hi>the beginning, and this l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fe manifeſt unto you which was to the Apoſtles? And if it be, why do you take a Text from the Letter, and Preach from it, and ſhew the People the Letter?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> This word and this life which is Chriſt, was mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in fleſh, <hi>Ioh. 1. 14. The Word was made fleſh.</hi> 1 Tim. 3. 16. <hi>God was manifeſted in fleſh:</hi> And this Word, and this life in fleſh was manifeſted to the Apoſtles; for there was a glory of Chriſt in fleſh, in reference to his mighty works which were done in fleſh, which never any elſe did but he, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3. 2. &amp; <hi>chap.</hi> 15. 24. And this glory was as of the onely begotten Son of God; and this glory they beheld, and all Saints have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held it, and do behold it, but not with bodily eyes as the Apoſtles did, but with ſpiritual eyes, with the eyes of Faith, <hi>1 Pet. 1. 8. Whom though ye ſee not, yet believing ye rejoyce, &amp;c.</hi> They did not ſee at that time, for Chriſt was aſcended: neither do Saints as yet ſee, becauſe the Heavens do yet contain him;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:166753:20"/> but they believe; and believing is called a ſeeing in Scripture. <hi>Ioh 8. 56. Abraham rejoyced to ſee my dayes.</hi> He did not live to ſee it with his bodily eyes, but he ſaw it by Faith, by which alſo the Apoſtles had the ſight of Chriſt; elſe they could have ſeen but the outſide of glory, and have been dazzled therewith, as the reſt of the Jewes were which ſaw him, and were not' able to judge whoſe glory it was that they ſaw. In this ſpiritual ſenſe Chriſt is manifeſt to us, ſo many of us as believe, and we have ſeen him by faith, and he is in us by his Spirit, and is life within us as a living Word that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth us.</p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding this we take a Text from the letter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the whole will of God, and minde of Chriſt is left us in letters; and bleſſed is he that readeth and conſidereth thereof, as it is contained and declared in letters, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1. 3. And Chriſt himſelf who was manifeſt to himſelf, did take a Text from the letter to preach things that reſpected himſelf, which the letter contained: And <hi>Philip</hi> he took that Text in the letter which the <hi>Eunuch</hi> was guided to read, and preached Chriſt from it. And though preaching be from the letter, that though we make ſomething that is written, or ſomething that is comprehended in letters, the foundation of our preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, upon which we bottom and build our diſcourſe; yet we preach not the letter, but ſuch ſpiritual truths as are contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it, reſpecting Chriſt, as Chriſt preached the glorious truths of himſelf: And <hi>Philip</hi> preached thoſe bleſſed my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious truths which concerned Chriſt, which have a vertue and power in them from the Spirit which accompanies them, and which is given to the Elect, whilſt ſuch truths written in words and letters are preached to them, by which ſuch perſons are quickned, who were before dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 6, 8. For if the Goſpel which is now left us in words and letters in the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles Writings, be hid from any, it is hid to them that are loſt, in whom the god of this world hath blinded the mindes of them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve not, leaſt the light of the glorious Goſpel ſhould ſhine unto them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 3, 4. And indeed, this Goſpel as it is now upon record in letters, and is become (as ſuch) a ſtanding rule
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:166753:21"/> to men, is hid from this Generation of men (ſo far as we can judge) who are the propounders of this Queſtion; and their deſign is to hide it from others, and to draw all perſons off from all that is written, to depend upon an unwritten word; ſome word immediately dictated to them, within them, proceeding from him, who is (as they ſay) the Word from the beginning, and is the life, and is manifeſted (as they give out) within them as to the Apoſtles: And in this ſort of men doth the Devil ſhew his ſpite, ſpleen, and malice, againſt the holy Scriptures.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="answer">
                  <head>Querie 11. <hi>And ſhew me where the Prophets did take a</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preach<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing from a Text, and the juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of it; And what anoynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtes have to Preach.</note> 
                     <hi>Text, and preach from it; but only Chriſt read a place, and ſaid, it was fulfilled, who ſaid he was anointed to preach; and which of you can witneſs you are anointed to preach by the living God, yea or no?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Prophets took not any Text to preach from it, becauſe they were to lay the foundation of preaching unto others, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 20. and other were to build upon it all that they ſhould preach; and therefore it was that the Prieſts and Levites did preach out of the Prophets; they read therein and gave the ſenſe; And the Apoſtles proved all things from the Prophets which they preached; And though they did not preach from one particular Text, yet they preached from many Texts, for they cited many to confirm their preachings. And the Apoſtles alſo, as wiſe maſter-builder, sinſtructed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately by the ſpirit, did in their Doctrine perform the ſame work, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>viz.</hi> did found the Faith of Believers upon their Preachings and Writings. And the Miniſters of the Word which were to ſucceed them, are onely to put their ſuperſtructure to it, bottoming upon that ground-work which they have laid; and therefore it is that both they and we take a Text, that the weight of our building may be laid upon it, and that all may ſee and be convinced that we preach not our own dreams, but what we have warrant for from the Writings of the Apoſtles and Prophets, with and to whom God ſpake, and that the truth of our Doctrine may be read
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:166753:21"/> of all men, being engraven upon ſuch Scriptures which we make choyce of; and by this means alſo, the idle extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gances of mens wits and fancies, which will never convince the conſcience throughly, are prevented.</p>
                  <p>But, why is the taking of a Text quarrell'd at, when yet it is confeſſed that Chriſt took a Text? And doth he not therein juſtifie us? What if the Prophets did not, yet if Chriſt did, will not his example bear out our practiſe? But theſe men make light of this pattern, detracting and diminiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (though they know the danger of it, mentioned, <hi>Revel</hi> 22. 19.) from the fulneſs of that Scripture that declares it, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. 16. to 23. They ſay that onely Chriſt read a place, but the Evangeliſt ſaith, That <hi>as his cuſtom was, he went into the Synagogue on the Sabbath day, and ſtood up for to read;</hi> and that then there was a Book delivered to him, and when he had opened the Book, he found the place that he would read, and then cloſed it again, and gave it to the Miniſter. They ſay, that Chriſt ſaid it was fulfilled; and as if this were all, they mention no more; but the Evangeliſt ſaith, That the people wondered at the gracious words which proceeded out of his mouth. And theſe things are obvious from this Text they mention; Firſt, there were publike places to meet in, which were called Synagogues; Secondly, there were dayes ſet apart for ſervice to be performed to God in ſuch places, which are called Sabbath dayes; Thirdly, there was a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter whoſe work it was to read out of ſome book of holy Scriptures to the people to inſtruct them thence. Fourthly, it is manifeſt that Chriſt approved of all this, and he liked this way ſo well, that he himſelf did go and do likewiſe, and did accuſtom himſelf to the ſame courſe of teaching the people, as that which was edifying to them, ſo that it was not once only done that Chriſt took a Text, but oftend one, his cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome was to read ſome portion of Scripture, and to preach out of it. And it is evident that Chriſt did not onely ſay, <hi>This day is this Scripture fulfilled in your ears;</hi> but many gracious words proceeded from him, tending (as muſt needs be ſuppoſed by any man that hath but the uſe of his reaſon) to clear it up to their capacities, how that Scripture in every
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:166753:22"/> part of it was fulfilled, by opening and unfolding the many branches of ſo plentiful and large a Text, and ſhewing how all things therein related unto, were accompliſhed in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, which might be a ſubject of many Moneths diſcourſe as Chriſt might have followed it.</p>
                  <p>But theſe men object, that Chriſt was anoynted to preach; and demand which of us can witneſs that we are anoynted to preach by the living God.</p>
                  <p>Chriſts anoynting was not by the pouring of any oyl upon his head after the manner of the High Prieſts anoynting, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133. 2. which was but a ſhadow of a more excellent Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction which Chriſt had. And the Prophet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. 7. doth but allude thereunto: But his anoynting was by the donation of the Spirit, and the gifts and graces thereof, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 32, 33. &amp; <hi>ch.</hi> 3. 34. by which he was enabled to the execution of ſuch Offices and works to which he was called, in redeeming a people to God, and eſpecially to preach the Goſpel, which in a very excellent and glorious way he effected, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4. 22. And all the Saints receive the ſame ſpirit, and gifts, and graces, every one according to the meaſure of ſuch a part, which they fill up in the body, and are Kings, and Prieſts, and Prophets to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as Scripture calls them. But thoſe perſons eſpecially whom God calls out to be to the body in place of eyes to guide them and direct them, God gives more of his grace and influence to, as appears from <hi>Eph. 4. 8. He aſcended up on high, and gave gifts to men, viz.</hi> ſuch men as he placeth in his Church for the work of the Miniſtery, and for the perfecting of the Saints till the end of the world; therefore Chriſt is not anoynted alone, but all whom he calls to the Miniſtery are anoynted alſo with the ſame ſpirit and gifts, and graces; onely he hath the preheminence, and hath an anoynment above his fellows, for he received not the ſpirit by meaſure, as thoſe who are his Miniſters and ſervants now do, <hi>Pſal. 45. 7. Ioh. 3. 34.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="answer">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:166753:22"/>
                  <head>Querie 12. <hi>Tell me why you ſing</hi> Davids <hi>Conditions and</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Scripture. Pſalms; the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</note> 
                     <hi>Experiences in Meeter, and when you read them, Hats you put on, and when you ſing them, Hats you put off.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw. Davids</hi> conditions and experiences are many times our own conditions and experiences, and then we ſing them not as <hi>Davids</hi> meerly, but as our own, by a ſpirit of Faith making application to our ſelves of what we ſing out of <hi>David.</hi> But many times its otherwiſe, that ſomething of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> inditing, and of his ſtate, and containing his experience, is the matter of our Pſalms, which we cannot ſo fitly apply to our own condition and temper, and many ſtumble at this and are offended; but its from ſome darkneſs in themſelves, for Pſalms are for inſtruction by the very deſign and ſcope of of God who dictated them and enjoyns them, as the Titles of very many of them: ſhew: And the Apoſtle enjoyns the Saints to teach and admoniſh themſelves in Pſalms and Hymns, and ſpiritual Song; and what ever the matter of them be, one end or uſe of them muſt be inſtruction to our ſelves from them, as from any other parts of Scripture. And the reaſons of ſinging them are ſuch as theſe:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. God would have us in our meetings to rejoyce in him, which is done in ſinging.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. God would have his word to be familiar to us, <hi>Col.</hi> 3. 16. it muſt dwell in us, and this muſt be ſhewed in ſinging; and would have us ſo much to delight in it, and to finde ſuch ſweetneſs in it, that we ſhould make our ſelves ſpiritually merry with it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Becauſe ſinging is that which raiſeth the Spirit, refreſheth the heart, moves the affections very much, God would have the Spirits of his people to be raiſed and refreſhed in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate meditation of his Word, what ever the ſubject matter be; For therefore it is that the Pſalms which <hi>David</hi> and other Saints compiled to be ſing, conſiſt of ſubjects of greateſt diverſity and variety. Some are Hiſtorical, ſome Prophetical, ſome are Hortatory, ſome are Precatory, others Deprecatory, others Laudative or Pſalms of prayſe, and the ſoul ſhould take
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:166753:23"/> pleaſure in all, and have the heart raiſed in the meditation of all; Do we not obſerve how a prophane carnal ſpirit will compile Songs of every kinde of matter, and will make it ſelf merry therewith? And ſhall not a ſpiritual heart ſing every thing that is a Pſalm, and is Divine and Spiritual, with an elevated and raiſed minde?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> But why moſt <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms be ſung Many ſtrick at that who will aſſent unto the ſinging of other Pſalms which are compiled by a ſpecial gift.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> There are reaſons which are weighty, which do carry thereunto.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Pſalms which were immediately inſpired by the Spirit of God are moſt Divine and Heavenly, and do contain the moſt admirable Doctrine.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Scripture is given for every uſe, to be read, ſung, pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ched out of, confened of, medicated on, and to be the matter of our prayers alſo: And thoſe parts of it which we finde to be Pſalms, we ought to make uſe of as Pſalms, and ſing them; And though we have liberty to ſing other ſpiritual Songs of our own or others making, after we have wel digeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, as well as to read other godly Books beſides the Scriptures; yet as our reading of other Books will not excuſe our omiſſion of reading the Scripture, ſo our ſinging of other ſpiritual Songs will not excuſe our omiſſion of ſinging Scriptures Pſalms.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms were brought into the Church of God in <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> time, and an expreſs command given to the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites to ſing praiſe to the Lord with the words of <hi>David,</hi> and of <hi>Aſaph</hi> the Seer, which is a preſident and a pattern for Saints to follow.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. There are Commands laid upon the Churches of Chriſt, and upon particular Chriſtians to ſing Pſalms, Hymns, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Songs unto the Lord, and nothing ſuggeſted unto them concerning the matter of them: And doth Chriſt put a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice upon uſe people, and nor afford them any ſtraw or matter to perform the ſame with? There was no need, elſe Chriſt would not have been wanting; There were Pſalms, Hymns, and ſpiritual Songs complied by <hi>David</hi> to their hands; for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:166753:23"/> ſuch Titles we ſhall meet with in the Book of the Pſalms; A Pſalm, of <hi>David</hi> familiarly a Song often, in Hymn ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, as in the Title of 145 Pſalm.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the Apoſtle to the Church at <hi>Coloſs,</hi> is to let the word of Chriſt dwell in them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in all wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, teaching and admoniſhing them ſelves in pſalms, &amp;c. what is this but a clear ſuggeſtion, that the word of Chriſt, which is ſome part of Scripture, ſhould be famliar unto them, and become the matter of their Pſalms for their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. For is there not firſt an injunction, <hi>Let the word of Chriſt dwell in your</hi> And is there not after wards a direction how to perfom it and one way is, by <hi>teaching and admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves in Pſalms</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. It is leſs warrantable, becauſe there is no preſident for it; and more dangerous becauſe of ſome evil conſequences that may attend it to bring in other Pſalms of mens compiling and not Scriptural, into the Church of God, and to impoſe them upon the people For the people that muſt act in ſinging, muſt firſt know them to be conſonant to the Scripture, and muſt have a right underſtanding of them, that they may ſing to their edification; and them there muſt either be a book of ſuch Pſalms ſo brought in and impoſed, which every Saint muſt have, or elſe the whole Church muſt be gathered together every time there is ſinging, to peruſe ſuch Pſalms which muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to be ſung amongſt them but Scripture is ſilent concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch wayes, and ſeemes to give other direction.</p>
                  <p>And though he that had a gift brought his Pſalm into the Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 26. yet for ought appears he ſung it alone, and then the reſt might judge, and ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> or not ſay <hi>Amen,</hi> as they approved or diſapproved of it; And it was not impoſed upon the Church to be ſung. But the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> layes ſinging of Pſlams, Hymns, and ſpiritual ſongs upon the whole Chruch, and there are no orders of Muſitians now, or office of ſinging Choriſton as in the Old Teſtment, but all the people are the Choriſters in the dayes of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, to ſing Pſalms and Songs, &amp;c. And the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> layes at injunction upon every particular Saint, <hi>if he be merry, to ſing Pſalmi, Jam.</hi> 5. 13. But hath every particular
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:166753:24"/> Saint a gift to compile a Pſalm? If not, what muſt ſuch a Saint do? Therefore there muſt of neceſſity be uſe made of Scripture-Pſalms.</p>
                  <p>And as for ſinging them in Meeter, the <hi>Hebrews</hi> had their Poetrie, according to which they both compiled and ſung their Pſalms: And it is but ſutable, that every Nation ſhould have the liberty of their own proper and peculiar Poetrie among themſelves to praiſe God by, and meeter is that which is congruons to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Poetry.</p>
                  <p>Concerning putting on of Hats in reading Pſalms, and putting them off in ſinging them, I ſhall not much conteſt; But this I ſay, that reverence is that which is ſutable to all Gods Ordinances, and becauſe the putting off the Hat doth ſhew reverence, it would be very comely when Scripture is read; but if it be otherwiſe, I judge it not to be want of reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in ſuch a perſon, becauſe reverence may be ſhewed, and not tied to one poſture, therefore I leave perſons to their liberty. Yet there is a difference in Ordinances; in ſome we have an immediate addreſs to God, and in ſuch we uſe more reverence, as when we pray or give thanks, we do not ſend one to God with our requeſts, but we go our ſelves to him immediately; but in preaching and reading it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, we have not immediate communion with God, but God ſends by whom he will ſend his Meſſage to us; and ſpeaketh not immediately, but by another; and ſo there is no irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, though the like degree of reverence be not given. And hence it comes, that we may uſe a different poſture and geſture, though the ſame words be ſpoken, if they be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in an Ordinance of a divers nature. As if words of prayer he read as a part of Scripture, then they are Gods ſpeaking to us by another, but if we our ſelves make uſe of ſuch words, and put them into our own prayers, then they become our ſpeaking to God, in our immediate addreſſes unto him, and ſo the Hat may be put on in the former, and yet ought to be put off in the latter; the like may be ſaid of ſinging and reading <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms: They are different Ordinances, and may require different poſtures. There is alſo difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ſpeaking and hearing; he that is the ſpeaker, though
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:166753:24"/> it be but in a civil Aſſembly, ſhews more reverence, ſpeaking to many, then they that hear him do to him, and is uſually uncovered, when they that are ſpoken to are covered, and in Religious Aſſemblies it is ſo alſo; he that ſpeaketh, though it be in the name of God, is uncovered, when yet the people that are ſpoken to are uſually covered; But in ſinging of Pſalms, they are all Speakers, and have to do with God, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their holy joy in him, and in his word, and therefore are all uncovered. But the cuſtome of the Churches of God in theſe things, if there be not palpable ſuperſtition in them, is much to be reſpected, and not raſhly departed from 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 16. and offence to brethren in ſuch things is vigilantly to be avoyded, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 20, 21.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="answer">
                  <head>Querie 13. <hi>Whether you have the voice, and whether you do know the voice of Chriſt from the voice of a Stranger? My</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">What is Chriſts voice, and how di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from a Strangers voice.</note> 
                     <hi>Sheep know my voice, ſaith Chriſt, ſeeing that you are ſo forward to judge, and ſit as Judges of the Saints Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Apoſtle tells us in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> that God who at ſundry times, and in divers manners ſpake in time paſt unto the Fathers by the Prophets, hath in theſe laſt daies ſpoken to us by his Son; for the Word was made fleſh and dwelt among the Jews, and went up and down teaching in their Synagogues, and preaching the Goſpel of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4. 23. and this Son of God in fleſh ſent forth the Apoſtles to preach, and put a word into their mouthes, and guided them by his Spirit in writing to the Churches what his minde and will was unto them, <hi>Let him that hath an ear, hear what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches.</hi> Now that which Chriſt preached, and the Apoſtles preached, and wrote unto the Churches, that is Chriſts voyce, as from <hi>Heb.</hi> 4 3. which is fetched out of Pſalm 95. appears. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>to day if ye will hear his voyce:</hi> What voyce was this? The Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Heb 4. 2. That unto us was the Goſpel preached aſwel as unto them but the word preached did not profit them, through unbelief.</hi> The word then which they heard in <hi>Davids</hi> time
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:166753:25"/> which was preaching out of the Prophets, was this voyce, and ſo the Goſpel which Chriſt and the Apoſtles have preached and left upon Record, is the voyce of Chriſt. And this voyce we have in the Scriptures, and this voyce we know, and we are able through Gods Grace to diſtinguiſh this voyce from the voyce of a ſtranger, if any bring not this Doctrine which Chriſt and the Apoſtles brought, we know him to be a Wolf and an Antichriſt, and after once or twice admonition, we dare not ſay God ſpeed to him. But there is another voyce which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe perſons who queſtion us, intend and pretend to, and that is an immediate voyce which ſpeaks within them, (as they ſay) and dictates unto them all that they ſay and do: Now this voyce we have not heard, nor do we know it within our ſelves experimentally, and we believe and hope that we ſhall be kept, that we may never know it. For we know it is not the voyce of Chriſt, but the voyce of a ſtranger. We know it from what it ſpeaks and acts in others, yea, in theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that pretend to it, and we bleſs our ſelves from it, for it is the voyce of the Devil, that comes as Chriſt to them, and pretends to be he, but deludes them, and deceives them, as one of themſelves, recovered out of their ſoares hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed. Now to the praiſe and glory of Gods Grace we ſpeak it, that we have neither heard his voice nor ſeen his ſhape.</p>
                  <p>Concerning our judging, there will be occaſion to ſpeak of it in the Anſwer to the next Queſtion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="answer">
                  <head>Querie 14. <hi>Whether that which is in you which Judgeth, be eternal and infallible, yea or no?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe men are harping in many of their Queſtions <note place="margin">Ifallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty further diſcuſſed.</note> upon one and the ſame ſtring; They have a conceit of Chriſt within them, ſpeaking within them, acting within them; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all, and doing all immediately and infallibly that is ſaid and done by them; ſo that it is not they that ſay or do any thing, but it is Chriſt and the Spirit within them. And this ſo fills them, that it almoſt fills all their Queſtions: Now it doth appear, that it is a ſpirit of deluſion, that thus poſſeſſeth them, becauſe it contradicts both Chriſt and the Spirit in the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:166753:25"/> Scriptures, in many things. And after this Chriſt and Spirit within, they enquire of us, whether that which judgeth in us be eternal and infallible; But we aſſert no ſuch thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our ſelves. For though all the Saints have the Spirit of Chriſt dwelling in them, which is eternal and infallible; yet that this Spirit ſhould do all that Saints do, and ſhould ſay all that Saints ſay, and ſhould judge for them, both of perſons and of things after an infallible manner; and that they ſhould neither ſay, nor do, nor judge any thing by any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of their own, but the Spirit, all this we deny. For the Apoſtle ſpeaks of himſelf, When I would do good, evil is preſent; ſo it may be ſaid of every man, when I would ſay or do right, errour is preſent. Notwithſtanding though we judge not either perſon or thing, by any Spirit of infallibility, yet there's one that judgeth, and that is the word which Chriſt ſpake, and which Scripture ſpeaketh; and this word is eternal and infallible; And ſo far as we judge according to this word, our judgement becomes eternal and infallible; and ſo we may ſpeak of perſons preſent condition with much certainty, becauſe we know what the Scriptures have ſaid of them. Chriſt tells us of Wolves, that ſhall come in ſheeps clothing, and that by their fruits we ſhall know them, <hi>Mat. 7. 15, 16.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> tells us who is an Antichriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> he that denyeth the Father and the Son, <hi>1 Joh. 2. 22.</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> propheſieth of falſe Teachers, that ſhall bring in damnable hereſies, denying the Lord that bought them, <hi>2 Pet. 1. 1.</hi> When therefore we ſee ſuch, we may judge of their preſent ſtate, what and who they be; but in reference to their future final ſtate, we muſt leave them to the judgement of God, who infallibly knows who are his.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15 and 16" type="answer">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:166753:26"/>
                  <head>Querie 15. <hi>What are the Ordinances which are ordained of God, that thoſe which you call</hi> Quakers <hi>deny? Or when did God command you to obſerve them, as to ſprinkle Infants, and to pray before and after your Sermons, (as you call them) or to ſet times, dayes and hours, which was in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration which were enemies to Chriſt, who obſerved ſuch things.</hi> Querie 16. <hi>What theſe Ordinances of God be which you</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">The juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of ſeveral ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſt in the Churches of God.</note> 
                     <hi>ſpeak of? and where God commanded them, and to whom: which you ſay them (which you call</hi> Quakers) <hi>deny? men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion them in particular, and declare them openly in Writing, and give over accuſing.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe two Queſtions are diſtinct in the paper pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to me, but the former entirely comprehends the latter, and is more ample then it, requiring us, not onely to ſhew reaſon of accuſing them, but alſo grounds for the juſtification of our own practiſe, therefore I have joyned them together; And in reference to the firſt; What Ordinances they do deny which God hath commanded, there is no need that we ſhould accuſe them, for they are accuſers of themſelves in their very Queſtions which they propound. The Reader may eaſily diſcern from them, what the things are, againſt which their malignity is ſhewed. It is againſt all outward teaching, againſt ſinging of Pſalms, againſt Miniſtery, againſt Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, expreſly againſt Infants baptiſm, againſt publick prayer, againſt all ſet times, dayes, and hours of performing religious duties, the 10, 11, 12, 15, 17, 18, 19. Queries do declare all this. Now whether theſe be Ordinances of Chriſt, and how they will be maintained ſo to be, will be the Queſtion, and for our own juſtification muſt be diſcuſſed. I have already given ſome touches, reſpecting outward teaching, and have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to clear up our practiſe in ſinging of Pſalms, and ſhall now attempt to vindicate other of our ways, and the ways of the Churches of Chriſt, from unjuſt exceptions, and diſcuſs them as I meet with them in the paper.</p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:166753:26"/>
                  <p>And firſt concerning ſprinkling of Infants, there is ſo much <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſprinkling of Infants.</note> written for and againſt this practiſe, that I accompt it loſt time to make any large debate about it; onely ſomething of that which ſatisfies us in reference to our own practiſe I ſhall preſent.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, for the Act of ſprinkling, we uſe it not, though ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing may be held out to juſtifie it; The blood of Chriſt is called the blood of ſprinkling, <hi>Heb. 12. 24.</hi> and cleanſing was by ſprinkling blood, <hi>Heb. 9. 13.</hi> and ſprinkling of blood was uſed in the Paſſeover, and ſignified cleanſing; therefore ſeeing water in Baptiſm typifies Chriſts blood, and the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of it ſignifies cleanſing from ſin, why may not the water be ſprinkled on the ſubject of Baptiſm, to ſignifie the cleanſing away of ſin by the blood of Chriſt. If any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject further, let ſuch as uſe it maintain it. Our practiſe is to uſe the water of Baptiſm in a waſhing way, which ſutes well with the myſterie in it, which is waſhing away of ſin, <hi>Act. 22. 16.</hi> And the Greek word which is put for baptiſm, is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to Tables, brazen veſſels, beds, and ſuch like things, which was not by dipping, but by the application of water in a waſhing way, <hi>Mar. 7. 4.</hi> So that though the word ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie dipping, yet it ſignifies waſhing alſo, which warrants the application of water in Baptiſm, in a waſhing way.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, for the ſubject of baptiſm, whether it be to be applyed to Infants, amongſt many things I ſhall onely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent this, <hi>viz.</hi> That Baptiſm is an outward Seal of an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and viſible Covenant of Grace, which runs always up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the condition of believing; and is to be applyed to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible believers or Saints, and is alſo to be extended in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the ſubject as far as the Covenant is extended; and if the Covenant be extended not onely to viſible believers, but to their whole Infant ſeed, as from <hi>Gen. 17. 7.</hi> compared with <hi>Exod. 12. 48, 49.</hi> and alſo from <hi>Deut. 29. 10, 11.</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, then the Seal of. it muſt extend ſo far alſo. I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm all this, firſt, that it is a Seal, for God having promiſed ſuch a bleſſing as the taking away of ſin in the Covenant of Grace, <hi>Jer. 31. 34.</hi> would (by the Ordinance of Baptiſm in the application of the element of water in a waſhing way
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:166753:27"/> to the body) have the baptized perſon to know and believe that he waſheth away the ſin of the Soul by the blood of Chriſt, <hi>Act. 22. 16.</hi> therefore it is ſaid, <hi>Act. 2. 38.</hi> be baptized for the remiſſion of ſins, not to effect it, but to aſſure it to you; ſecondly, that it is an outward Seal, becauſe all is external and viſible; the water is, which is as it were the Seal; the waſhing is, which is as it were the Sealing, or the putting on of the Seal; the body is, which is as it were the thing ſealed; all is outward, and done before men; but whether it be done in the conſcience really and inwardly by the Spirit, that is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and known to God. And the Spirit onely is the inward Seal that aſſures the heart. And many times, the outward confirmation is ſeparated from the inward aſſurance, as in <hi>Simon Magus;</hi> he had the outward ſign of remiſſion of ſins, but not remiſſion of ſins it ſelf. Thirdly, that it is an outward Seal of an outward and viſible covenant of Grace, becauſe the profeſſion of faith, with ſhews of reality, is all that is required unto the bringing of perſons into it, and unto the participation of the Seal of it. It was enough to the Eunuch he profeſſed his Faith, and <hi>Philip</hi> baptized him; he could not ſee into the heart to know the truth of it, yet he baptized him; And <hi>Ananias,</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on brought them within the Covenaut, and gave them a right to the Seal of it, and not any truth of Faith it ſelf, for there was none: And indeed that Covenant wherein the miniſtery of man in made uſe of, in the making of it, muſt needs be external. Fourthly, that it is extended in reference to the ſubject of it as far as the Covenant is excended, becauſe it is the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of it, to the ſubjects of it; and the confirmation muſt need be as large as the Covenant; but this is not doubted of by any. Fifthly, that the Covenant is not onely extended to viſible Believers, but alſo to their whole Infant ſeed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in <hi>Gen. 17. 7.</hi> we finde it ſo; for it runs in theſe words, <hi>I will be thy God;</hi> now this is comprehenſive of all bleſſings, even the very higheſt, as <hi>Heb. 11. 16.</hi> ſhews, and it is the ſame for ſubſtance with that in <hi>Jer. 33. 33.</hi> which is called a new Covenant; And Circumciſion that ſealed it, is called The Seal of the righteouſneſs of Faith, <hi>Rom. 4. 11.</hi> and the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:166753:27"/> of the fleſh did ſignifie the circumciſion of the heart, <hi>Col. 2. 11.</hi> And the Gentiles that profeſſed <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Faith, which had nothing to do with <hi>Canaan,</hi> entred into it, and ſpiritual priviledges were ſealed to them, <hi>Exod. 12. 48, 49.</hi> by which it appeareth to be a Covenant of Grace: And for the ſubject, it was with <hi>Abraham</hi> a Believer, and with his ſeed; what ſeed? his whole Infant ſeed; for the application of the ſeal, <hi>viz.</hi> Circumciſion to the whole Infant ſeed, ſhews that the Covenant extended it ſo far; And <hi>Deut. 29. 10, 11.</hi> clears it, That the Covenant was with the little ones. And though all Infants are not counted the ſeed as to ſpiritual and eternal bleſſings, as indeed neither are all that profeſs Faith with ſhews of reality (as <hi>Demas,</hi> &amp;c.) to be accounted the true ſpiritual ſeed, yet they are the ſeed as to Church privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and external Ordinances of a ſpiritual nature, and ſo were all <hi>Abrahams</hi> Infant natural ſeed, and Believers ſeed in all Ages the true ſeed, as to the enjoying of ſuch Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</p>
                  <p>Concerning praying before and after Sermon; firſt, we <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before and after Sermon.</note> finde that in the meetings of the firſt Chriſtian Church at <hi>eruſalem,</hi> there was Doctrine, breaking of bread, and prayers, in which Ordinances that Church of Chriſt was converſant, <hi>Act. 2. 42.</hi> Secondly, we finde that the Apoſtles, whoſe work was to attend upon the Miniſtery of the Word, upon that account caſting off ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing of Tables, did joyn prayer unto it, and did wait upon theſe joyntly, <hi>Act. 6. 4.</hi> Thirdly, we reade that it was the Cuſtom of the Apoſtles to begin every weighty ſerious buſineſs with prayer; when they were to caſt a lot, they went to prayer firſt; when they were to lay on hands on Deacons, they firſt prayed; when they were to ſend forth <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> to the work which God had appointed them unto <hi>viz.</hi> to preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, they prayed firſt, &amp; when they ordained Elders in every City, they began it with prayer; ſo that all was attempted with prayer; preaching therefore being a weighty work, ſhould be performed with Prayer. Fourthly, prayer is that which ſanctifieth all things, and perſons have a Chriſtian holy uſe of things which in their nature are but Civil. <hi>Every</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:166753:28"/> 
                     <hi>creature of God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul)</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 5. is ſanctified of God by the word and prayer; much rather ſhould holy and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious ſervices be uſed holily, by adioyning prayer thereunto. Fifthly, The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> giving direction in his Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> how the worſhip and ſervice of God ſhould he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on in the Churches of Chriſt, doth in <hi>1 Tim. 2. 1, 2, 3.</hi> enjoyn, that firſt of all Prayers and Supplications ſhould be made; his ſcope is not to direct particular Chriſtians, but Churches of Chriſtians in their publike Aſſemblies; as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from <hi>verſ. 11, 12.</hi> where Women are commanded to keep ſilence, and are not ſuffered to teach. Now this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects the publike meetings of the Saints, and in <hi>1 Cor. 11. 4.</hi> the ſame Apoſtle gives light how publike exerciſes of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion were carried on in the Chriſtian Aſſemblies, there was prayer and propheſying afoot amongſt them; propheſying was not without prayer. Sixthly, there are alſo many gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral rules (amongſt others that in <hi>Phil. 4. 8.)</hi> which ſerve to juſtifie this practice: <hi>What ever things are juſt, true, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, pure, lovely, of good report, if there be any vertue, any praiſe, think on theſe things.</hi> Now I leave it to the judgement of any perſon who is not given up to a wicked ſpirit, whether prayer before and after preaching be not ſuch a thing. And the Apoſtle many times requires, that things which make for edification may be done: <hi>1 Cor. 14. 4, 5, 12, 26. Eph. 4. 26. 1 Theſ. 5. 11.</hi> But theſe men ſhew what ſpirit they are of, by their arguing againſt the moſt religious and holy Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, and ſpiritual Performances which the Saints uſe, and which the Devil and the Fleſh have alwayes much oppoſed.</p>
                  <p>Concerning ſet times, days and hours, which was in the <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſet times, and days and hours.</note> generation which was enemies to Chriſt, who obſerved ſuch things, I know not what anſwer to make, unleſs I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood what it is that they find fault with: The Charge runs as if we did keep up thoſe Jewiſh Sabbaths, and holy Faſts, and Feaſts, and Hours of Prayer which were obſerved in Chriſts time whileſt he lived on Earth amongſt thoſe of his own Nation, moſt of which were enemies unto him; but they are, or might be convinced of the contrary concerning us, that we ſet no ſuch times a part for worſhip as they did;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:166753:28"/> neither was it the practice of the enemies of Chriſt only to ſet ſuch times, and days and hours apart, but of the friends of Chriſt alſo, and of Chriſt himſelf while he was upon the Earth, and of the Apoſtles, ſeeing it was by divine inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution that the people ſhould meet at ſuch times, <hi>Acts 3. 1.</hi> Nor was it any part of their enmity againſt Chriſt, but rather of their ſubjection to God, that they met at ſuch times; therefore theſe Perſons have another intent and ſcope in their queſtion. It is our Lords day-meetings, and our Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faſts, and Thankſgiving-days that we keep, that they are offended at; it is the hours of prayer in our Church-meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Families which they find fault with: and in this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo they ſtrike at Godlineſs; for if they can but deſtroy all forms, the power will fall with it; for though the form be but the ſhell, yet it preſerves the kernel; the power is put forth in a form, and if they can but acquit and diſcharge the body from ſervice and religious exerciſe, the ſpirit will not bear up in it any long time after, but all devotion and duty Godward both in body and ſoul will fall in ſhort time; Therefore the Devil and his Inſtruments plead againſt ſet times, days and hours, knowing very well that Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip cannot at all be performed by many Chriſtians together, without times, and days, and hours, no nor yet kept alive any long time in any.</p>
                  <p>But for the better juſtification of ſet times, days and hours <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the firſt day.</note> for Gods ſervice, let it be conſidered; Firſt, that time is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual adjunct of action: there is no action can be done, but it muſt be done in time; It is therefore a neceſſary adjunct of divine and ſpiritual actions: ſo that if God will enjoyn a worſhip and a ſervice to be performed to him, he muſt needs enjoyn the time in which he will have it performed. Secondly, let it be duly weighed, that both the Apoſtles themſelves were wont to meet upon the firſt day of the week to worſhip God, and that Chriſt met with them upon that day twice, and thereby ſhewed his approbation of their meeting upon that day: <hi>Joh 20. 19, 20, 26.</hi> And alſo that the Churches that were planted in the world by the Apoſtles, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that day in courſe as it came, and ſet it apart for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:166753:29"/> exerciſes; 1 <hi>Cor. 16. 1, 2. Act. 20. 7.</hi> and further it is to be obſerved, that the Apoſtle annexed duty to that day, and bound the collection of the Saints to that day as it ſhould come in courſe; which how he could do without uſurping upon them, unleſs he had received it from the Lord, I cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. And alſo that that day above all other days was deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated the Lords day, and it was ſpoken of as a noted known day to all the Saints by that name <hi>Rev. 1. 10.</hi> which name <hi>(Lords day)</hi> doth point at an inſtitution; as, when the Supper is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominated the Lords Supper, it is from the inſtitution which it had from the Lord Chriſt that it is ſo named; and Lords day holds the ſetting of it apart to the Lords uſe, and to call ſomething for remembrance, which can be nothing but the reſurrection, as the Lords Supper is for remembrance. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, let it be obſerved that occaſional Faſts are juſtified in the <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning faſts and thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving days.</note> New Teſtament as well as in the old, from Primitive ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples both of Apoſtles and Churches, <hi>Acts 13. 3.</hi> and 14. 23. and upon the like accompt will occaſional thankſgivings be maintained: and we have in the new Teſtament, beſides the inſtances that may be fetcht from the Old Teſtament, ſomething that looks that way. <hi>Acts 4. 23.</hi> to 32. Fourthly, concerning hours, it doth not appear from the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment what hours were ſpent in their publike ſervice, nor <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hours in the publike ſervice.</note> whether thoſe hours that were ſpent were ſpent together, and at one entire meeting without intermiſſion and parting: or whether they divided their hours according to the pattern and example which they had in the Offerings and Sacriſiees of the Old Teſtament, which were not at once and together, but at diſcontinued times; there was a morning and an eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning-Sacrifice, which were offered about the third and ninth hours; and there was a great expediencie in it, that there might be ſome bodily refreſhing betwlxt the times, and the neceſſity of Nature was provided for in it, and Sabbath-exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes were diſtinguiſhed thereby from Faſts; and upon this accompt, it is equitable that Chriſtian ſervice ſhould be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried for time after ſuch manner: but herein Chriſtian Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath the Principal ſtroke; for we do not judge our ſelves Scripturally obliged to ſo many hours, or ſo diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:166753:29"/> that ſome ſhould be in the forenoon and ſome in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon; but for conveniencies-ſake we practiſe it, yet not preciſely keeping to an hour. And for hours in Families, we <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning time ſpent in holy exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes in Families.</note> have read how holy men of God have carried it in their milies: <hi>Abraham</hi> commanded his children and his houſhold after him, and they did keep the way of the Lord: <hi>Jacob</hi> he reformed his Family, and purged away the Idols and all the filth from it, that they might more purely ſerve the Lord to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: <hi>Joſbua</hi> reſolved that he and his houſe would ſerve the Lord, now he could not reſolve it in reference to ſecret worſhip, which each apart was to perform to God; but it refers to Family-duties and ſervice, which ſhould be on foot amongſt them together: And <hi>David</hi> would walk not in his own Perſon alone, but in his houſe with a perfect heart: And there is a Propheſie that reſpects Families mourning apart, which is to be accompliſhed in the dayes of the Goſpel. <hi>Zach 12. 12.</hi> to the end, And there is a Promiſe made, where two or three are gathered together, (ſuppoſe in a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily or any other way) Chriſt will be in the midſt of them; and where Saints are together in a Family, the Spirit of God within them will be a Spirit of Prayer within them, and will bring them together; and there cannot be Family-duties but there muſt be a time to perform them in and if morning and evening be taken for them, it is moſt congruous: Firſt, becauſe occaſions, wilt then beſt permiso for it will be before the works of these Callibas be begun, and it will be afree they are finiſhed, Secondly all things are ſanctified by prayer, and ſo will their is bours be in the morning, and their reſt in the evening; But where or when doth a good heart diſpute againſt theſe things? a ſpiritural heart will rather dictate to a Perſon to apprehend the opportunitigs unto prayer and all other ſpiritual duties, both apart and with others, and will practiſe what was commanded in reference to preaching, will pray in ſeaſon and out of ſenſon, at times which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eiency makes cheice of; and at other times alſo will put up all manner of prayers, and at all times, as occaſion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quites; And where Saipts are together they will encourage one another, and ſay, come let us joya together, and pray,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:166753:30"/> and ſeek the face of God in prayer, and in other duties alſo; and in Families eſpecially will this be done.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="answer">
                  <head>Querie 17. <hi>Whether you do not ſeduce the People to araw</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Spirits teaching, in what way to expect it. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the outward muſt be denyed, that the inward may be received.</note> 
                     <hi>them from the anointing within them? when as</hi> John <hi>ſaith, they need no man teach them, but as the anointing, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe was Eternal Life to him that did abide in the anointing.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> The ſcope and intent of this Queſtion, is, to overtura all out ward teaching by men, &amp; to erect an immediate teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Spirit in the room of it; It is to carry men off from Gods outward Ordinances, to wait for ſecret Inſpirations of God; and indeed it is to ſubject men to Satanical deluſions in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the Spirits ſuggeſtions. For that which is inſinuated, is this, <hi>viz</hi> that the drawing of any people to attend upon any out ward inſtruction, becomes in effect a withdrawing of them from the annointing, or from that inward teaching of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, (which indeed) hath not one ſyllable of truth in it: For <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt did draw the people after him, ſo did Chriſt, ſo did the Apoſtles, to hear the Word of God which they preached, which was an outward word, an outward teaching: did they withdraw ſuch Perſons from the inward teaching, from the annointing within them? or were they not rather drawn to the annointing within them, by attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and giving heed to the outward preaching? did not the Spirit of God accompany their outward preaching? did not <hi>John</hi> come in the Spirit and Power of <hi>Elias</hi> in his outward Miniſtery? and were not many turned from their diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the wiſdom of the Juſt? and could this be without the Spirit? was there not an admirable power of the Spirit attending both Chriſts teaching, and the Apoſtles preaching? did their outward inſtruction withdraw the people from the Spirit, or did they not rather convey the Spirit to them? Is not the Goſpel as it is preſented to men in an external way, ſaid to be the adminiſtration of the Spirit? 2 <hi>Cor. 3. 8. Gal. 2. 5.</hi> And were not many annointed with enriching gifts by that Spirit, which is the Spirit of the Goſpel, which comes along with the Goſpel preached? How then are any ſeduced by being
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:166753:30"/> being brought to the hearing of the Goſpel preached? or are not they rather ſeduced who are drawn off from the external Means and Miniſtery, by which the Spirit is given, and Faith is wrought, to wait for the receiving of the Spirit without any Word to conveigh it to them? which Spirit when they have, it is not the Spirit of Truth, but of Deluſion: as is confeſſed by one of their own, newly redeemed out of ſuch helliſh cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, under which theſe poor Creatures are held.</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>But they produce a Scripture which ſeems to erect and ſet up one only Teacher, which is the Spirit, and to throw down and caſt under foot all outward Teaching which is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by men.</hi> John <hi>ſaith to them he wrote, 1 Ioh. 2. 27.</hi> That they needed not that any man teach them, but as the annointing teacheth them of all things, and is Truth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, This is not ſpoken of all men, but of thoſe <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2. 27. Anſwered. <hi>viz.</hi> ye need that no man teach you, but as the anointing teacheth you all things.</note> who are come to Chriſt, and had the Spirit, that they needed no man to teach them; But what muſt they do that have not the Spirit? how muſt they obtain it, if not by the Word of the Goſpel which conveys it? therefore an outward teaching is neceſſary for ſuch. Secondly, The Apoſtle ſeems to ſpeak of ſuch an annointment which they had received, which had already taught them, by which they ſhould abide in Chriſt and not be ſeduced; as thoſe words ſhew, <hi>Even us it hath taught you, you ſhall abide,</hi> &amp;c. Now indeed the Spirit of God hath taught us of all things in the Scriptures which were of his inſpiring: whereto if we attend, we ſhall abide in the Truth, and not be miſled by Seducers; and to this teaching of the Spirit in the Scriptures, we need not that any teaching of man ſhould be added, but as we are taught in them. Thirdly, The words, <hi>You need not that any man teach you, but as the annointing teacheth you,</hi> are hyperbolical expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; there is an exceſs in them, as in many places of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptute, as where it is ſaid, <hi>If all things ſhould be written, which Jeſus ſaid and did, the whole world would not contain the the Books that would be written:</hi> The meaning is, there would be very many Books written, if all ſhould be written;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:166753:31"/> And in verſ. 20 of this very Chapter, the Apoſtle tells them that they knew all things; it is an exceſſive ſpeech, for no one knoweth all things but God: Chriſt himſelf as man knew not all things, who yet had the Spirit not according to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but beyond it; the meaning then is, they had much knowledge, and knew many things, and ſo they needed not that any man teach them; that is, they knew ſo much already of the Doctrine of the Goſpel, that if onely they perſevered in that which they knew, they might be kept without much teaching; it is to be underſtood in a comparative ſenſe; not in an abſolute conſideration, as to exclude all teaching, but to exclude much of that teaching which others do require; and it reſpects the abundance of knowledge which they had in compariſon of Believers of former times before the Goſpel was revealed; as from the Propheſie, from which theſe words of <hi>John</hi> were fetcht, appears, Jer. 31. 34. <hi>They ſhall teach no more man his Neighbour, and every man his Brother, ſaying, know the Lord, for they ſhall all know me from the leaſt of them unto the greateſt of them; ſaith the Lord;</hi> Knowledge ſhould ſo abound in the dayes of the Goſpel, that they ſhould not need teaching ſo much as in the times of the Law; For it points at the days of the Goſpel after Chriſt ſhould be revealed; of which Chriſt ſaith, <hi>That he that is leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven, ſhould be greater then</hi> John <hi>the Baptiſt,</hi> who yet was greater then al the Prophets, ſo exceedingly ſhould Light ſhine in Goſpel-times; but that teaching ſhould be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely excluded, was not the Apoſtles meaning; for though they never did need it leſs, yet they never had it more then in the days of the Apoſtles and of the Primitive Churches: For there were many who were eminently gifted beſides Paſtors and Teachers, who did teach; And it is to be obſerved, that the Spirit was never given ſo plentifully in any Age, as in that Age, wherein ſo much outward teaching was; ſo that there is no ſuch meaſure of reception of the Spirit, that can thruſt out outward teaching while we are here: yea, and <hi>John</hi> himſelf thought there was need of teaching, while he tells them of an unction that they had received, and that they knew all things, and needed not that any one ſhould
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:166753:31"/> teach them; for verſ. 36. he ſaith, <hi>Theſe things have I writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten unto you in reference to them that ſeduce you;</hi> that is, leaſt you ſhould be carried away from the Truth by them, he taught them to ſtand faſt in the Truth they had received. Fourthly, It holds forth that they were not, neither ſhould be Babes, which knew nothing themſelves, were able to judge of nothing themſelves, but do depend wholly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally upon others to teach them, and were led wholly as others guide them; in this ſenſe they ſhould not need teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for there was a light ſet up in their ſouls, and they had the Spirit of God, which is a light, and enables them to diſcern with ſuch clearneſs, that they believe not becauſe others tell them ſo, but becauſe they can look into the Truth themſelves. Concerning the laſt words of that queſtion: <hi>viz. that the Promiſe was eternal Life to him that did abide in the anointing,</hi> becauſe there is no ſuch Scripture that ſaith ſo, and becauſe no courſe we take in our teaching doth tend (as hath been ſhewed) to withdraw from the anointing; therefore I ſhall not inſiſt upon them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="answer">
                  <head>Querie 18. <hi>Whether you do not bewitch the people, and draw them from the Spirit of God within them, to obſerve thoſe</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Miniſtery, maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and other practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meetings.</note> 
                     <hi>things which God never commanded; to tell the people of a Sacrament, and following your outward Teaching, who ſtand praying in the Synagogues, and are called of men Maſters; which Chriſt d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d forbid,</hi> Mat. 23. <hi>And have the chiefeſt places in the Aſſemblies; Whether theſe be not called Antichriſts, which act contrary to the Commands of Chriſt, yea or no?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> In this Queſtion, beſides the repetition of former things, they ſtrike at Sacraments, at the teaching and praying of Paſtors and Elders, for to them they ſpeak in al their queſtions; at the poſture of ſtanding in prayer, at the places of meeting, calling them Synagogues in a deriſive way, at the Title of Maſter, which is put upon them, and charge them with ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in aſſuming chiefeſt places, which (they ſay) ſuch take; I muſt clear up the truth in all theſe particulars.</p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:166753:32"/>
                  <p>Firſt, Concerning Sacraments: there are no Ordinances on foot amongſt us which we call by that name, though there <note place="margin">Concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</note> might be a defence for it; but there are Ordinances which others call Sacraments, and we call them Seals of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which are to confirm Faith in the Covenant of God, concerning Remiſſion of ſin by the blood of Chriſt, and other Grace of the like nature, which is vouchſafed in Chriſt; and they are Baptiſm and the Lords Supper, and they are both of them inſtituted by Jeſus Chriſt: <hi>Mat. 28. 19. 1 Cor. 11. 23.</hi> and they both point at Chriſts Death and the ſhedding of his Blood, <hi>Rom. 6. 3. 1 Cor. 1. 26. Mat. 26. 28.</hi> and they ſerve to Seal Remiſſion of ſins by Chriſts Blood, <hi>Act. 22. 16. Mat. 26. 28.</hi> and indeed both of them are to put us in remembrance of Chriſt; and that which Chriſt hath inſtituted, who dares abrogate? And thoſe that deſtroy the Seals, therein attempt the deſtruction of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; for Seals are the ratification of Covenants; or at leaſt they do deſpiſe Gods grace of condeſcendency, who for the cauſe of our weakneſs in belief of his Covenants, vouchſafeth to grant us Seals to confirm them. And Gods Covenants have never been without Seals; and though there hath been change of Seals, yet Seals are as old (one or other of them) and are to laſt as long as the Covenants, and the Lords Supper expreſly till Chriſt come: <hi>1 Cor. 11. 26.</hi> And let all take heed, leaſt ſlighting Seals and gracious Covenants, they be hereafter accompted deſpiſers of Gods Grace, which will be reckoned amongſt the greateſt ſins.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Concerning our outward teaching, I have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red already in part the neceſſity of it; It is the ordinary way <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward teaching and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery.</note> by which a people that are in darkneſs are brought to light: <hi>Mat. 4. 13, 14. Act. 26. 16, 17, 18.</hi> It is the way and means by which the deep and profound, and many moſt ſweet and neceſſary Truths of Scripture come to be underſtood: <hi>Acts 8. 30, 31.</hi> It is the means which God hath appointed for the bringing of men to Faith: <hi>Rom. 10. 14, 17.</hi> It is the power of God to Salvation: <hi>Rom. 1. 16. It pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſs of preaching to ſave thoſe who do believe: 1 Cor. 1. 21.</hi> Upon which accompt it is, that the Apoſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:166753:32"/> wo unto himſelf, if he preach not the Goſpel of Chriſt: <hi>1 Cor. 9. 16.</hi> It is the means of exalting Chriſt: which made the Apoſtle ſo much to rejoyce that Chriſt was preached, though from an envious Spirit: <hi>Phil. 1. 18.</hi> And hence it is, that God in all times and ages in which he hath had a Church, hath had ſuch which have preached and taught the people; as <hi>James</hi> obſerved in that ſpeech of his in the Councel: <hi>Act. 15. 21. Moſes</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of old time hath in every City, them that preach him, being read in the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue every Sabbath-day.</hi> And muſt Chriſt be worſe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for then <hi>Moſes?</hi> no; Chriſt himſelf was a Preacher of himſelf, <hi>Luk. 4. 18. Mat. 4. 23.</hi> and he gave Commiſſion to his Diſciples to preach, and ſent them into all the World for that purpoſe; <hi>Mat. 18. 19.</hi> and in them he commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned others in all Ages to the end of the World; for he promiſed his preſence to the end of the world, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently not to them only which were not to continue ſo long, but to ſuch alſo who ſhould ſucceed them impreaching. If any one ſhould attempt to make this place invalid, by inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting the words which are tranſlated, <hi>to the end of the World,</hi> to be meant only <hi>to the end of that Age,</hi> becauſe of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of the ſenſe that is put upon the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which is tranſlated <hi>(World)</hi> and ſometimes ſignifies <hi>(Age)</hi> to ſhew the weakneſs thereof. I ſhall only give this hint, theſe words together <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> are uſed for the end of the World in a plain proper ſenſe in many places of Scripture; as <hi>Mat. 13. 39, 40.</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d <hi>cap 24. 3. Heb 9. 26.</hi> and I know not that they are together uſed in any other ſenſe.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, It ſeems to be too groſs and wicked to reſtrain Chriſts preſence to an Age, much more the things that are given in charge to be preached and obſerved verſ. 20. as if one only Age were to obſerve Chriſts Commands: for how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Apoſtles were the Perſons that immediately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Commands, and had the Promiſe, yet there is a further ſcope in Chriſts words, and a clear intimation of the continuation of the work by others, who ſhould ſucceed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they ſhould ceaſe to be. For ſutable to this, is that charge which <hi>Paul</hi> gives to <hi>Timothy.</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 13, 14. <hi>I give the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:166753:33"/> 
                     <hi>charge in the ſight of God who quickeneth all things, and before Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c. that thou keep this Commandment without ſpot irrebukably, until the appearing of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Was <hi>Timothy</hi> to continue til the appearing of Jeſus Chriſt, or is there not another thing implyed, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> ſhould have ſucceſſors in that work? to whom <hi>Paul</hi> gives the charge as well as to him, and lays it upon them to keep the ſame Commandment: And becauſe it is one work, <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks to them all as to one man, and ſo did Chriſt in the Commiſſion above mentioned. <hi>And Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, up on high and gave gifts to men, and he appointed ſome Apoſtles, ſome Evangeliſts, ſome Prophets, ſome Paſtors and Teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtery, and for the edifying of the Body of Chriſt, till we all come to the unity of the Faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God, unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the Stature of the falneſs of Chriſt.</hi> Eph. 4. 11, 12, 13. that is, till all Saints come to a State of Perfection, ſo as neither to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to errour nor to ſin, which is not attainable in this World; Chriſt was born in weakneſs and littleneſs of ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as other men, and he grew up to a perfect man; the Apoſtle alludes to this: Saints are growing up whileſt they are here in knowledge and in all ſpiritual Gifts and Graces, till nothing be wanting of that proportion which God hath appointed for them, which is not in this life; And Miniſtery muſt laſt while Saints are in their growing ſtate, while any thing is wanting of the meaſure they muſt come unto.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> But miniſterial gifts are not now to be found in the world, ſuch which the Miniſters of the Goſpel had in the Primitive times; the Apoſtles were not to go forth into the world, but were to tarry at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> though they had a Commiſſion to Preach the Goſpel in all Nations, till they were firſt endued with power from on high, that is, till they were annoynted with the holy Ghoſt, as was done at the time of Pentecoſt, as is mentioned <hi>Act.</hi> 2 1, 2, 3. &amp;c. then had they the Spirit given them, and were enriched greatly with gifts, by which they were enabled to diſcharge that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice they were called unto; ſo <hi>Gal. 3. 5.</hi> the perſon that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:166753:33"/> preached the Goſpel, had the miniſtring of the Spirit, but now no ſuch gifts; therefore no ſuch work miniſterial as was then, nor any ſuch Officers, as Paſtors, Teachers, &amp;c. as was then.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, When the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> layeth down the qualification of Biſhops or Elders (for they are one) he mentions many things reſpecting a good converſation, and ſome other things reſpecting a right diſpenſation; <hi>he muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ound in the Faith, and ſetled and eſtabliſhed in the Truth, and mighty in the Scriptures, that he may convince gainſayers;</hi> and inclinable to communicate what gift he hath, by an apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to teach, and he muſt be good and upright in his life in all things; But not one word proceeds from the Apoſtle of any extraordinary gifts wherewith he is to be endued, but a total ſilence in that point: Now if ſuch an anointment had been neceſſary with ſuch an abſolute neceſſary, as that without it there could be no Biſhops, no Paſtors and Elders of any kind at all; how comes it that the Apoſtle omits the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo main a thing which is made the principal, when he nominates many other things? Therefore that anointment which the Apoſtles had, and thole gifts wherewith they were enriched, they ſerved for other ends then to qualifie them for the Miniſtery; Or if ſome of them were Apoſtles qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which were to go into all the world to preach the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and did therefore ſtand in need of tongues, yet they were not Paſtors and Teachers qualifications which are fixed to certain places and people; Such gifts as were then given, were teſtimonials that Chriſt was received to the Glory of the Father, and did ſit at his right hand, and that all power was given him to Heaven and Earth, according as he ſpake when he was upon the Earth.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, There might be as forcible an argument fetch: againſt all Chriſtianity (if words be taken up in the Letter, in which they run) as againſt Miniſtery, Mark 16, 17. <hi>Thoſe ſigns ſhall follow them that believe in my name, they ſhall caſt out Devils, they ſhall ſpeak with new tongues,</hi> and many other things it is ſaid they ſhould do, and they did ſo in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times; very many of them, and perhaps all had one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:166753:34"/> gift or another; as, 1 Cor. 12. 7. <hi>The man i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the Spirit is given to every man to profit withall; to one in one kind, and to another in another kind.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when <hi>Paul</hi> met with Diſciples at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> the firſt Queſtion that he asked them, was; <hi>whetherthey had received the holy Ghoſt ſince they believed?</hi> As if ſuchgifts of the holy Ghoſt had been ſo connexed to Faith, that they could not be ſeparated the one from the other ſhall we therefore reaſon from hence, that becauſe theſe ſigns are not now ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying thoſe that profels Faith, that there are no Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers to be found in theſe latter Ages? We may as rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with as much (and more) colour of Scripture rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon after ſuch manner, as theſe perſons do againſt Miniſtery.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, the Apoſtle ſpeaks of Miniſtery which ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have received, <hi>Rom. 12. 7.</hi> and requires a waiting upon it, and he that teacheth muſt wait upon his teaching, and he that exhorteth muſt wait upon his exhortation: Here is not only an outward teaching allowed, (which the perſons who ſhaped theſe queſtions oppoſe) but an outward teaching by office is enjoyned, which ſome others that are no Quakers are ready enough to withſtand; For if it ſhould be meerly by a gift, which ſome will grant, though they deny Office: How comes it that the Injunction is to wait upon it? For though it be not expreſly in the Original, yet it is neceſſarily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, that there may be ſenſe made of it; and how comes an injunction of maintenance, <hi>Gal. 6. 6.</hi> from him that is taught, to him that teacheth, if teaching be not by Office, be not waited upon, and made the ſpecial work of ſome perſons? And how comes the Apoſtle to raiſe a living to ſome perſons from their preaching, when he ſaith, that they who preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel, and ſaith alſo, that ſo the Lord hath ordained it? <hi>1 Cor. 9. 14.</hi> and if perſons make it not their office, and wait upon it as upon their office, if only they preach by vertue of a gift that they have, or think that they have and exerciſe it at their pleaſure, will the Apoſtle have ſuch men live upon the Goſpel that ſo preach it? Or why doth the Apoſtle fetch an argument from them that ſerved at the Altar, whohad their livelihood thence,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:166753:34"/> to prove a living upon the Goſpel Preached, if ſuch who were to Preach the Goſpel, were not Miniſterially and by office to do it; For thoſe who lived upon the things of the Temple, and upon the Altar, were Prieſts and Levites, and Miniſters of the Old-Teſtament. Were all theſe Directions and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions which reſpect Office, Temporary and Tranſitory? Then may the whole Goſpel in all the Injunctions and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of it be made a Temporary, and a Tranſitory Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>Or can any rational perſon conceive how Preaching is like to be kept up, and to be on foot any long time, if ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons be not appointed to wait upon it, and if it be not laid upon ſome perſons as their work? Or what certainty can the people be at concerning ſupply that way, if none be engaged to it? And how weakly is Preaching likely to be carried, when none attend upon it, nor give themſelves over unto it? The Apoſtles who had incomparable endowments beyond any who live now, did yet give themſelves to prayer, and to the Miniſtry of the Word. And ſhall not thoſe who fall great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly below them, be much rather wholly devoted to that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, when as the work is ſo weighty if it be carried as it ought to be, that it requires the whole of man?</p>
                  <p>But I believe theſe dayes wherein there is ſuch arguing againſt Miniſtry, and ſuch pleading for the Preaching of gifted men, were Propheſied of by <hi>Paul, 2 Tim. 4. 3, 4.</hi> where <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 3, 4. which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects the heaping up of Teachers, opened.</note> he ſaith, that <hi>the time ſhall come, when they will not endure ſound Doctrine; But after their own luſts, they ſhall heap to themſelves Teachers, having itching ears; and they ſhall turn away their ears from the Truth, and they ſhall be turned unto fables.</hi> It is obſerved that the Greek word that is tranſlated <hi>(heaping)</hi> doth import three things: 1. An ardent ſtudy to acquire many Teachers. 2. A raſh and heady gathering to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether of many Teachers, without any ſolid judgement exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed. 3. A confuſed multitude of ſuch as are gathered together imployed. And it may be further obſerved, what manner of perſons they be that ſhall heap together Teachers after this manner, and what grounds they go upon. Firſt, They are ſuch who will not endure ſound Doctrine. Secondly, they are ſuch
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:166753:35"/> who pleaſe their own luſts and fancies in the Teachers whom they heap together to themſelves. Thirdly, They are ſuch who have itching ears, who affect to hear many, and no one nor a few will ſerve their turn; they hear one and another without being ſatisfied, after the manner of thoſe who have an itch upon them. Fourthly, They turn away their ears from the Truth, and are turned to Fables; that is, any thing that is new, though it be a very fable and have no truth in it, is thirſted after by them; old truths will not pleaſe ſo well, they leave them, and turn after theſe. It is alſo worthy to be conſidered how Teachers come to be multiplyed, that there is ſuch an heap of them; why the wantonneſs, looſneſs, and vanity of the ſpirit of the People, which will not endure the ſtrictneſs of the care and vigilancy of Paſtors and Teachers, and have alſo itching ears, ſhall multiply them and pile them up one upon another like an heap; the luſts of the people make many Preachers more then any thing elſe. And theſe perſons that are ſo wanton that they muſt have many, are yet ſuch who will not have ſome, <hi>viz</hi> ſuch who are ſolid and preach the Truth; For this Text ſaith, they turn away their ears from the Truth (where it is ſolidly held forth) and are turned after fables.</p>
                  <p>Nothwiſtanding that there is a diſtemper of this kind which is very prevalent in theſe dayes, yet I dare not ſo affix preaching to office, as thereby to exclude all exerciſing of gifts; but the exorbitancy is that which I appear againſt; I would have thoſe that do preach, and others alſo that are ſolid ſober Chriſtians, judge together who are fit to preach, and who have a gift; <hi>1 Cor. 14, 32.</hi> and I would have them firſt proved, before approved, <hi>1 Tim, 3. 10.</hi> and then they ſhould exerciſe it occaſionally; for he that hath an office, it belongs to him and is his part to wait upon it; but he that hath only a gift without an office, muſt look unto it how he is called out to exerciſe it before he uſe it.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Not only outward teaching offends them, but <note place="margin">Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</note> praying ſtanding will not down with them; I know not what poſture they would have, but that which we intend by it, is, that he that prayeth may be ſeen by all the people on whoſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:166753:35"/> behalf he prayes; For he is their mouth, and it doth affect the heart of the people when their eyes behold him who is pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them, and it is juſtified from <hi>Solomons</hi> example, who when he prayed on the behalf of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he ſtood in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of all the Congregation, and ſpred forth his hands to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven; And yet we plead not ſo for ſtanding, but that we ſhall grant other poſtures to be lawful, provided that the perſon that prayeth be viſible to the people; but they that love not the duty it ſelf, but except againſt it as in Querie 15. may better be allowed to find fault with the poſture.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Nor will they be pleaſed with the place of <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Suna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues.</note> meeting, who would have no meeting at all for ſuch exerciſes; they call them Synagogues in way of deriſion; but there is no harm in that word if they underſtood it; it doth but ſignifie a place where the people come together, a place of Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling; It did ſignifie the place where the Jews met together to hear the Word of God upon the Sabbath-day. It was no holy place in the Jews accompt, as the Temple was; it was not hallowed and ſanctified for ſacred uſes only as the Temple was; but was made uſe of for civil purpoſes, as to puniſh offences; For they ſcourged ſuch as they counted malefactors in their Synagogues, <hi>Mat. 23. 34.</hi> If our place therefore be only like a Synagogue, its no brand to us; ſome place we muſt have if a ſervice be to be done; &amp; one place will ſerve our turn as well as another, provided it be a capacious place that will hold the company that are to meet in it, and that it be alſo a free place, which we may make bold with without detriment to any, and a known agreed-on place, which all may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, and may repair thither: yet our place cannot hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be called a Synagogue in alluſion to the Jewiſh Synagogues; for it was not erected for any ſpiritual or divine uſe, or with any intent of ſerving God in it, as the Synagogues among the Iews were, though they made uſe of them for other ſervices.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, After cavelling at places, they come to ſtrike at <note place="margin">Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Title of Maſter.</note> Perſons, and charge us with Ambition and Affectation of Honour: 1. Becauſe we are called Maſters. 2. Becauſe we have as they ſay, the chiefeſt places in the Aſſemblies; for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:166753:36"/> the former, <hi>viz.</hi> the title, we confeſs it is put upon ſome of us, and as we have not affected it, ſo neither have we cauſe to reject it. It doth import nothing but civil honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect which others ſhew us: It is put upon all perſons who have either birth, breeding, riches of this world, office and employment of an honourable nature: It was not only put upon Chriſt, but upon the Apoſtles of Chriſt alſo, in <hi>Joh. 12. 21.</hi> and not rejected by them. Some came to <hi>Philip,</hi> and ſaid (Sir) <hi>we would ſee Jeſus:</hi> It is in the Greek, <hi>Maſter,</hi> we would ſee Ieſus: and <hi>Acts 16. 30.</hi> The Gaoler came to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> and ſaid, (Sirs) that is in Greek, <hi>Maſters, what ſhall</hi> &amp;c. and they repelled him not in reference to that Title.</p>
                  <p>But theſe Perſons alledge <hi>Mat. 13.</hi> where it is ſaid; <hi>Be not ye called Maſters, for you have one Maſter which is Chriſt.</hi> But this Text will ſtand them in no ſtead; for this word that is tranſlated <hi>(Maſters)</hi> is, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which ſignifies ſuch Maſters as are <hi>Duces viae,</hi> Guides of ones way, and <hi>Guberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores vitae,</hi> Governours of a mans life, which is proper to Chriſt, and not to any man; For no man doth-it, ſaving in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentally from and under Chriſt. And <hi>Rabbi</hi> which was forbidden them alſo, verſ. 8. is ſuch another Title, which carries too much in the ſignification of it; it imports one Teacher who for the abundance of his knowledge is inſtead of many: And the affectation is that which is principally forbidden, and the derogating in the coveting of ſuch-Titles from God in that Glory which is due to him, who is that <hi>Dux viae,</hi> that Guide of Guides, and that <hi>Rabbi,</hi> that one teacher which is more then all; But for the Title <hi>Maſter</hi> in a civil acception, there is neither hurt in giving of it, nor in taking of it, provided that pride and haughtineſs do not oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion it; For the Apoſtle ſaith, in giving honour, go one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another, <hi>Rom. 12. 10.</hi> And we know that he juſtifieth the Title of <hi>Maſter</hi> in all ſuch who have others to ſerve them, and gives direction unto them how they ought to deport themſelves towards thoſe who are their ſervants. But theſe perſons may better be born with, if they deſtroy Titles, who deſtroy Relations themſelves which founded them. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:166753:36"/> chief places in the Aſſemblies, except the Pulpit be the chief place, which the great ones covet not, I know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the cauſe of this charge, but do account it a meet ſlander.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="answer">
                  <head>Querie 19. <hi>Whether a man ſhall ever grow up that he need no man teach him under your Miniſtry, yea or no? ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Apoſtle ſaith, you need no man teach you; and you which have been long Teachers, how many have you brought up into this Condition?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Perſons may grow up under the teaching of ſuch a Miniſtery as is among us, to need no man to teach them, in the ſenſe in which the Apoſtle underſtands it; they may be brought to the knowledge of all the great truths of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and may come to underſtand many of the high and deep things of Scripture; they may alſo come to be much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and eſtabliſhed therein, ſo that in a comparative ſenſe they may not need Teachers; not that they are abſolutely perfect in knowledge, but that they know very much, and are able to teach others alſo; and of this we have ſome experience. But in the ſenſe in which theſe perſons underſtand it (for they intend ſuch a perfection in knowledge as excludes all igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and all humane helps for any further attainments) we ingenouſly confeſs, that no man is ever like to grow up ſo high, as to need no teaching, nor are we our ſelves come up to ſuch a perfection; and we think our ſelves to be but Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in knowledge, in compariſon of that which we hope to attain unto in heaven; nor do we think it any diſhonour to us to confeſs ſo much, eſpecially while we medicate upon the Apoſtles expreſſion, 1 Cor. 13. 12. <hi>Now we ſee through a glaſs darkly,</hi> ſpeaking of the time of this life, <hi>but then we ſhall ſee face to face,</hi> ſpeaking of the time after this life. Nor do we find that Chriſt himſelf, or the Apoſtles, ever bred up perſons to ſuch a condition as theſe men ſpeak of, to need none to teach them in their ſenſe. <hi>Paul</hi> bred up <hi>Timothy,</hi> and to a great height he bred him under his Miniſtery, whom he cals Son, becauſe he had been with him as a Son, yet he exhorts
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:166753:37"/> him to meditate upon ſuch things, and to give himſelf wholly unto them, that his profiting might appear unto all, <hi>1 Tim. 4. 15.</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> exhorcs thoſe that he wrote to, of whom he Iaith, that he did ouly put them in remembrance of things, and that they knew them already, and were eſtabliſhed in the preſent truth, that they would grow in grace, and in the knowledge of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>2 Pet. 3. 18.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Concluſion that they put to all theſe Queſtions, is this;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Church of Chriſt</hi> (ſay they) <hi>is a pillan and ground of Truth, which doth witneſs the eternal Spirit; and if you be the ſame Church, and have the ſame Spirit, anſwer me theſe Queries without any conſequencies or ſenſes; otherwiſe diny your Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Paſtorſhip, and to be no Church of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Church of Chriſt is the ground and pillar of Truth, and doth witneſe the truth of all that is contained in the holy Scriptures, and more eſpecially that the myſterie of godlineſs is gteat, <hi>viz. That God was manifeſt in the fleſh, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in the Spirit, ſeen of Angels, preached unto the Gentiles, believed on in the World, received up into Glory.</hi> And this we aſſert without any Conſequencies or ſenſes; many of which, (if not all) you that urge us thus, moſt deſperately deny. As for your queſtions, we have anſwered them agreeablyto Scripture, and have made ſuch inferences and neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences, and have put ſuch ſenſes as cannot be contradicted by any knowing Chriſtian, nor indeed by any but thoſe whoſe deſign is to deſtroy all Scripture, and utterly to ſubvert the Faith of the Goſpel, and to lead men captive after their own deluſions: and inſtead of denying a Paſtorſhip, and Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and our ſelves to be the Church of Chriſt, we ſhall pray God to open the eyes of ſo many of theſe poor creatures, who are thus ſold over to deluſions, that ſo many of them as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Gods Election, may be recovered out of the ſnare of the devil, who are led captive for the preſent after his will.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:166753:37"/>
               <head>A Coppy of a Letter which <hi>Richard Waller</hi> a Quaker, ſent to a Gentlemans Family, near <hi>Stockport</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire:</hi> in which both he and his wife had been formerly ſervants: Wherein he pleads for an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute perfection, and for Quaking.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>MY dear love in the Lord preſents it ſelf unto you all in the power of the truth; deſiring the Lord to eſtabliſh you all in the truth it ſelf, that you may grow and become faithfull unto the Lord to bring forth much fruit, that the Lord in all things may be glorified by you. Dear friends, I did long ſtand in oppoſition againſt a company of people by the World called Quakers; So it pleaſed the Lord in his time to let me ſee my condition; So that I did plainly ſee that I had got the Saints words to talk of before I came to witneſs the Saints condition: Now the Scripture ſaith, Jeſus Chriſt was made manifeſt to deſtroy the works of the Devil. Whoſoever can witneſs Chriſt manifeſt in him, can witneſs ſin deſtroyed: But he that ſaith Chriſt is manifeſt in him, and committeth ſin, is a lyar. For whoſoever is born of God, ſinneth not, <hi>1 Job. 2. 4.</hi> For his ſeed remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in him, and he cannot ſin, becauſe he is born of God; Now the Prieſts of the World tell us we cannot be perfect here: So they leave a hole for Satan here contrary to Scriptures; and when will they have him caſt out? As for me, I deny all the Teachers of the World: For I can really witneſs that I have found my Teacher within me, which is a myſterie to all the World. Now, I and the reſt that can witneſs that Chriſt is made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:166753:38"/> in us, we are hated of the World; for we diſown the Worlds ways, Worlds worſhips, and Worlds Cuſtoms, and they diſown us. Now the Scriptures ſaith, <hi>He that is a friend to the World, is an enemy to God:</hi> The World calls us witches and mad men; they did ſo by Chriſt; they ſaid he was a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil: and they ſaid <hi>Paul</hi> was mad, and <hi>Stephen</hi> ſpoke Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy: It is juſt ſo now as it was then; they Jear and ſay, Never any of the Saints Quaked and Trembled. Read theſe Scriptures at your leaſure, and you may find them lyars, <hi>Heb. 12. 25, 26. Ezra. 9. 3, 4. Heb. 12. 21. Moſes quaked and trembled. David trembled Pſal. 119. 120. Pſal. 18. 7. Heb. 3. 16. When I heard, my belly trembled, my lips quivered. Jerem. 23. 9. Iſa. 66. 2. Ezek. 32. 10. Dan. 10. 7.</hi> and <hi>11. Daniel Trembled, Acts 9. 6. Joel 2. 10. Job 26. 11. Amos 8. 8. Jer. 30. 6, 7. Acts 13. 40. 41.</hi> See here is a Cloud of Witneſſes againſt them: And whereas they deny that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is to be attained, here they are found lyars. See <hi>Phil. 3. 15,</hi> Let us, as many as are perfect, be thus minded. <hi>Col. 1. 28. Col. 4. 12. 2 Tim. 3. 17. Heb. 6. 1. Heb. 10. 14. He. 12. 23. Heb. 13. 21. Jam. 1. 4. Col. 4. 12. Deut. 18. 13. Joh. 17. 21. I in thee, and thou in me, that they may be made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in one.</hi> I plainly ſee the Prieſts taught deceit, and we believed them: But the Lord hath diſcovered their deceit to his, and he will teach all his himſelf. Oh therefore wait upon the Lord, and ceaſe from man whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, and mind the light of God in you which diſcovers deceit; and the peace of God be with you all, and keep you all in the ſenſe of him ſtaid in your minds, that you may be kept in his feare which keepeth the mind clear, and pure, and open to receive his teachings, and to forſake the evil, and chooſe the good, and ſo bring you into obedience; and it will ſuffer you to joyn with nothing but what is of it own nature, pure and clear, and it will keep you from the evil of the World. The Lord cauſe you all to grow up as trees of Righteouſneſs, and ſtabliſh your hearts in the living truth, that his name in all thing may be glorified.</p>
               <p>Dear friend Chriſtian, I have ſent you a little book, read it without partiality, and you may ſee deceit diſcovered; My
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:166753:38"/> wife deſires you to preſent her ſervice to her Maſter and Miſtreſs, and all the children, and her love unto you and all the ſervants; We are both well, and our child grows faſt. As for me, as I begun with my dear love unto you all, ſo I end: For I dare not complement, becauſe it is a Cuſtom of the World. Farewell,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Copy of an anſwer to the forementioned Letter, written in the name of the Church of <hi>Duckenfield,</hi> now meeting in <hi>Stopport,</hi> and ſent unto the wife of <hi>Richard Waller,</hi> for the ſetling and eſtabliſhing of her in the faith of Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a member of the forementioned Church, wherein all ſuch Scriptures which were brought to prove an abſolute Perfection and Quaking are Interpreted, and the true ſenſe given to them; and freed from ſuch corrupt fenſe for which they are alledged.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Siſter <hi>Waller,</hi>
                  </salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOu are very precious to us, though your miſcarriage againſt God and us hath been very great. We are apt to hope that the Lord either hath or will convince you of the ſin you committed in your unadviſed Marriage; Which you ſo ſelfwilledly carried on againſt us: And when your heart is kindly humbled; we know you will give praiſe to God, and juſtifie us: And then we ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive as much can ſee of joy from your repentance, as we have done grief from your ſin: We cannot yet think otherwiſe, but that you do belong to the Lord: And if ſo, he will not ſuffer you to have reſt in any evil way you have gone
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:166753:39"/> in, till he have made you truly ſenſible, and ſorrowfull after a Godly manner: which if ever you once manifeſt to us, we ſhall with as much tenderneſs own you, as in any time heretofore: For you are very dear to us, and our bowels do very much yearn after you: Eſpecially ſince we heard of a Letter which your husband wrote to <hi>Duckenfield,</hi> which ſome of us have ſeen; by which we diſcern what deadly poyſon he hath ſucked in, to the undoing of his poor Soul, if God be not very mercifull to him, and bring him to Repentance. And you alſo, through your nearneſs of Relation to him, are expoſed to multiplicity of Temptations, to forſake the faith of our Lord Jeſus, and to turn aſide to ſuch Satanical deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which he is carried away with. We do conceive hope, that as yet the Lord hath kept you, by obſerving one paſſage of his Letter, which holds out your deſire, that your ſervice may be preſented to your Maſter and Miſtreſs: therein, owning the relation they ſtood in to you, and you to them, which he declares againſt, making it the worlds way, and not Gods. Our deſire and prayer to God for you ſhall be, that he will yet keep you even to the end. And who can tell but that the Lord may bring out a great deal of good to your ſoul, by this evil of your Husbands fearfull apoſtacy, which his Letter holds out? God may open your eyes, thereby to ſee your ſinfull haſte which you made in that Marriage: He may humble you for ruſhing upon it againſt Counſel; he may make you to know that he was angry againſt you, by leaving him to ſuch fearful error of way. He hath laid a ſore affliction upon you, by giving up one ſo near and dear to you, to ſuch fearfull Temptations. You have offended God through him, and now you muſt be chaſtned in him. Be awakned, be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakned, and conſider the Lords righteous hand in this matter; The perſon whom you have choſen, God ſeems to have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken; at leaſt for a time he is become the Devils Captive. O fear you, and repent you, leaſt he alſo forſake you. But we hope better of you; and our prayer is, that you may be ſetled and eſtabliſhed in the truth. We foreſee that you will be ſtrongly ſollicited: He that thought himſelf bound to tempt perſons by his Letters at ſo great a diſtance, what al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luring
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:166753:39"/> ways will not he take to cauſe you to forſake your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, and to turn aſide to ſuch fleſhly deceits of Satan: take heed you be not bewitched with pretences, and quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Scripture preſented in the Letter; there lyes the greateſt danger. The Devil tempted Chriſt, by telling him that it was written; and his Inſtruments will uſe the ſame fleights: They will put falſe Gloſſes upon Scripture, while they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny all ſenſes to be put upon Scripture, to deceive themſelves and others thereby. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Pet. 3. 16.</hi> that ſome that are unlearned, and unſtable, do wreſt Scripture to their own deſtruction; and he doth warn them, leſt they being led away by the error of the wicked, do fall from their own ſtedfaſtneſs, by ſuch means. And we alſo do beſeech you to beware of this Snare, <hi>viz</hi> of Scripture abuſed by miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions. It is a miſconſtruction, when the conſtruction is made to follow the ſound of the words, though it be never ſo much repugnant to other Scripture: You know that all Scripture is given by Inſpiration of God, <hi>2 Tim 3, 16.</hi> And that holy men ſpake as they were Inſpired by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>2 Pet. 1. 21.</hi> Now God is a God of Truth, and the Spirit is a Spirit of Truth, and cannot ſpeak contrary things, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict himſelf: therefore, if there be any ſeeming contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in Scripture taken in the Letter of it, we muſt ſeek after a right ſenſe, by which the ſeeming contradiction may be removed. Your husband produceth many Scriptures to prove an abſolute perfection without ſin; And the firſt Scripture he mentions, is <hi>Phil. 3. 15. Let us</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul)</hi> (ſpeaking of himſelf and the <hi>Philippians) as many as be perfect, be thus minded;</hi> He Collects from hence, that the Saints here have ſuch a perfection that excludes all ſin: Alas poor Creature! We thought he had been better acquainted with his own heart: But he might have looked a little higher in the Chapter, upon <hi>ver. 12.</hi> and have diſcerned that <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly denies Perfection in reference to himſelf <hi>Not as though I were already perfect,</hi> ſaith he; <hi>Was Paul perfect, and yet was he not perfect?</hi> In the Letter there is a contradiction: But <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking by the Spirit of God, cannot contradict himſelf: therefore, we muſt look after the ſenſe of the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:166753:40"/> word <hi>[Perfect]</hi> It is many time taken for ſincere, <hi>2 Kings 15. 14. Aſa took not away the high places;</hi> that was his failing; Yet his heart was perfect; In what ſenſe perfect? Was it perfect without ſin? Not ſo, For it was his ſin that the high places were not taken away; But perfect, that is Upright; He did not ſerve God in pretence, but in truth, They ſay we muſt not give the ſenſe of Scripture, but muſt take it in the Letter; but that is contrary to the examples of Scripture. Thoſe in <hi>Nehemiah 8. 8.</hi> read in the Book of the Law, and gave the ſenſe; and it is neceſſary ſometimes to avoid contradiction, which is in the Letter, to give the ſenſe; The ſenſe of that place, in <hi>Phil 3. 15. Let us ſo many as be perfect, be thus minded,</hi> is this, Let us ſo many as be Sincere, Upright, and halt not betwixt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> betwixt the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel, be thus minded:</hi> that is minded like to <hi>Paul,</hi> as he had given them example; For that was the Scope in that whole Chapter; he had left the <hi>Law</hi> and all confidence in Mofaical Ordinances, and followed <hi>Chriſt;</hi> But yet was not perfect therein, as to be without defect in that, but was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and ſincere therein; and he preſſeth them, as many as were perfect, that is, upright, to be as he was, to do likewiſe, and yet not to think that they can be ſo compleat as not to need to follow more and more after Chriſt; but to be ſtill ſtriving, as he was; This is clearly the ſenſe, by which your husband may underſtand his error. As for all other places, to give a particular Expoſition of each Quotation, will take up more time then we can well ſpare at preſent; but as need ſhall require, upon intimation given us, we ſhall be willing to hold forth the ſenſe of any Scripture you ſhall doubt of hereafter, as the Lord ſhall help us, and we hope with Truth. comparing Scripture with Scripture, that one may not oppoſe another. Onely in general it is good to take notice that is Scripture there is mention made of a Comparative per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; Thoſe who ſtuck in <hi>Moſes</hi> his Rites, and could not get paſt them, were not ſo perfect as thoſe who were clearly bottomed upon the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> And to this Perfection <hi>Paul</hi> endevoured to bring the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> and <hi>Philippians,</hi> and all that did believe, <hi>Col 1. 28.</hi> And thoſe who were Babes in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:166753:40"/> knowledge, were not ſo perfect as thoſe who had their ſenſes exerciſed to diſcern betwixt good and evil, of which <hi>Heb. 6. 1.</hi> And there is a perfection that reſpect Juſtification, and not Sanctification, <hi>Heb. 10. 14.</hi> By one Offering he hath for ever perfected them that are Sanctified; that is, he hath perfectly juſtified all the Saints, by dying once; when as all the legal Offerings (though repeated day by day) could not do it; But there was ſtill a Conſcience accuſing for ſin. And there is a perfection that reſpects rather the number of Graces, then the meaſure of them, and reſpects rather duration and continuance to the end, then any height or ſtrength in the act of performance; as <hi>Jam. 1. 4.</hi> Let patience have its perfect work, that ye may be perfect and entire, wanting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; This perfect work of patience, is the work of patience perpetuated, and laſting to the end; He that endureth to the end ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Mat. 10. 22. Mat. 24. 13.</hi> And [being entire and wanting nothing] reſpects the filling up, and compleating the reſt of the Graces that they had, with this Grace of patience exerciſed to the end; as in <hi>2 Cor. 8. 7:</hi> Therefore as ye abound in every thing, in Faith, and Utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and knowledge, and in all diligence, and in your love to us; ſee that ye abound in this Grace alſo. When all Graces be in Saints, and do abide in exerciſe to the end, then there is a kinde of Perfection in Saints. And the Scripture doth frequently ſtir up the Saints to endeavor after perfection; When yet it ſaith not that is is to be attained unto in this life. <hi>2 Cor. 13. 9.</hi> We wiſh (ſaid the Apoſtle) your Perfection; and <hi>Heb 6. 1.</hi> Let us go on to perfection; And the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle himſelf was not Perfect, but going on towards it, <hi>Phil. 3. 12.</hi> Not as though I were already Perfect; But I forget that which is behind, &amp;c. and ſo follow on towards it. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, that while he was here, he did ſee through a Glaſs darkly; and that now, that is in this life, he did know but in part; and if but in part, where then was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection? And the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> tells all Saints, <hi>1 Joh. 1. 8.</hi> that if they ſay they have no ſin they deceive themſelves, <hi>and the truth is not in them;</hi> And the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> faith, <hi>that in many things we-offend all;</hi> he and all others did offend And he faith, he is a perfect man, that offendeth not in word; that
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:166753:41"/> is, he would be comparatively perfect that could only bridle his tongue; but who can do it at all times? we perceive your Husband cannot; for then he would never have uttered ſuch reproachſul words againſt godly men, calling them Prieſts, and ſaying they are found Lyars; his Conſcience will tell him that ſome of them are ſuch as fear the Lord: but he faith, if Perfection be not here, we leave an hole for Satan; and when will it be, if it be not here in this Life? Alas, alas, is he left ſo ſoon to ſo great darkneſs as not to believe another Life and World after this? that he asks when it will be, if not here? It ſeems Satan hath had an open door to enter into his heart, and fill it with ſuch fogs and miſts of Darkneſs; he might have read and weighed the Apoſtles words, in <hi>1 Cor. 13. 9, 10, 11. Now we know in part, but when that which is perfect is come, that which is in part ſhall be done away;</hi> and he might have conſidered that diſtinction of time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in theſe words, <hi>Now we ſee through a glaſs darkly, but then face to face;</hi> this [now] is here, and this [then] is after this life; But he ſtrengthens himſelf in that place, in 1 Ioh. 3. 9. <hi>He that is born of God, ſinneth not, but his Seed remaineth, and he cannot ſin;</hi> This he urgeth, but he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidereth not that the ſame <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith that which is contrary to this, <hi>viz. Whoſoever ſaith he hath no ſin, deceives himſelf, and the truth is not in him;</hi> A ſound ſenſe therefore muſt be brought out of <hi>Iohns</hi> words, elſe <hi>Iohn</hi> will be found a Lyar againſt himſelf, and againſt God, as your Husband endeavours to make him, denying ſin to be there, in whom Chriſt is made manifeſt, from this text; but the meaning is of ſin in courſe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſted and continued in, without true repentance and turning from it; he that is born of God cannot ſo ſin; for the ſeed of Truth and of Grace within him, will not let him ſo ſin; for after ſuch manner the wicked of the world ſin, but the Saints cannot ſo ſin; there will be ſmitings of heart in them, and they will ask and enquire what they have done, and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and turn to God, as <hi>Iob</hi> did, <hi>David</hi> did, <hi>Peter</hi> and all the Saints have done.</p>
               <p>Now concerning quaking and trembling, there is a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying of many Texts of Scripture without knowledge; for none of them can be applyed to juſtifie the practice of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:166753:41"/> thoſe whom they call Quakers. The firſt Text that they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, if it be taken in the Letter, as they take all Scripture, doth deſtroy them and their practice; <hi>viz. Heb. 12. 26</hi> whoſe voice then ſhook the Earth, but now he hath promiſed, ſaying, Yet once more I ſhake not the Earth onely, but the Heaven alſo. Now the Apoſtle gives the ſenſe of theſe words [yet once more] verſ. 27. It ſignifieth (faith he) the removing of thoſe things that are ſhaken, that thoſe things which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſhaken may remain: Now thoſe Perſons whom they call Quakers, they are ſhaken in their meetings, firſt one, and then another; then the Text taken in the Letter, ſhews that they ſhall be removed and taken away, ſeeing they are ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; but others who are not ſhaken, ſhall remain; ſo they fall by the Text which themſelves alledge. But the true ſenſe of this Text is Metaphorical, and ſignifies the removing of things corrupt in Church and State, ſo far as it remains yet to be fulfilled; and it did ſignifie the removal of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law of Rites, that the Goſpel might be eſtabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed inſtead there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. There was an outward ſhaking of the Mount, and of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but it was typical of this Metaphorical and ſpiritual ſhaking, and ſhewed how <hi>Moſes</hi> Paedagogie, or Childiſh Diſcipline was to be removed away; but what is this to their purpoſe? There is alſo a ſpiritual trembling, ariſing from the reverence of God and his Word, which is inward in the foul, which all Saints have more or leſs; <hi>Iſa 66, 2. Ezra 9. 4.</hi> which are Texts of his citing, but they make nothing for the upholding of their outward ſhaking: nor are they perſons that tremble at the Word of the Lord, but are deſpiſers of it, There is alſo a quaking and trembling of Fleſh, but it did ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe from the ſenſe of Gods Judgements, <hi>Pſal. 119. 120. Jer. 23 9, Ier. 30 5 6.</hi> and from a ſenſe of Gods Wrath; <hi>Pſal. 187.</hi> but they who have the name of Quakers, being all of them perfect and without ſin (as they pretend) cannot be afraid of Gods judgements &amp; of his wrath, nor do they quake upon that account; what they ſhall do hereafter if they repent not, we leave to that one ludge of the world to determine in his time. There is alſo a quaking from Viſions and Apparitions, as when an Angel appeared to <hi>Daniel, Dan. 10. 7. 11.</hi> and the outſide of the Viſion, thoſe that were with him ſaw, and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:166753:42"/> and fled through fear; they ſaw not the inſide, as thoſe that were with <hi>Saul</hi> did which ſaw a light, though they ſaw no man, and they were terrified. And <hi>Paul</hi> was aſtonied, and trembled <hi>Acts 9. 6.</hi> upon the appearance of Chriſt to him. Now whether theſe perſons pretend to apparitions or not, we know not; and whether there be any Apparition un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Devil doth appear, we know not; onely this we know, Thoſe perſons who ſaw many Viſions, and to whom God immediately, or by an Angel ſpake familiarly, which cauſed quaking and trembling, they were ſuch, for whom, and by whom, God wrought many wonderful things; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid the Phariſees to the people, We know that God ſpake with <hi>Moſes;</hi> It was known to all, by ſigns and wonders that <hi>Moſes</hi> did, that God had Communion with him and ſpake to him; ſo alſo it was with <hi>Daniel, Peter, Paul,</hi> and all others; ſo that all might be aſſured that God ſpake with then, and the appearance was viſible alſo: Now when theſe perſons can confirm their Viſions by miraculous things wrought for them and by them, it will be better received, that God hath appeared and ſpoken to them. But that which moſt ſatisfies us, that neither they nor their quaking are of God, is firſt, becauſe though ſome particular perſons, upon ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and ſudden appearances have trembled and quaked, yet there is nothing in all the Scripture that makes out the meetings of many people together in a conſtant way and courſe, waiting and expecting to ſee or hear ſomething which caſts them into trances, and brings upon them quaking and trembling, and in a kind of order alſo; as firſt one, and then another. Indeed the Apoſtles did abide waiting at <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> once; but never after, for the receiving of the Spirit ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Promiſe of the Father, by Chriſts own ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Injunction; but then the Spirit came in viſible manner; there was a ruſhing wind, and ſound from Heaven, and an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of cloven tongues, like as it were fire ſat upon every one of them, and they ſpake with tongues; But what injunction have theſe men to meet, and ſit together waiting for any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of ſpirit, or Angel, or ought elſe? And what promiſe have they made to them, or what outward appearance is there of any comming of the Spirit to them? Or what mighty
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:166753:42"/> works are done by them; Or what communion with God, or with his Spirit can they have, which oppoſe God in their many blaſphemous aſſertions which come from them? and who deſtroy many of the great Doctrines of the Goſpel? and who change and ſubvert Gods Ordinances, <hi>viz.</hi> Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions betwixt Magiſtrates and Subjects, Maſters and Servants, &amp;c. which God doth build up in his word?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Siſter,</hi> You may diſcern what little ſtrength there is in thoſe many Scriptures in your Husbands Letter, heaped toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, by that which we have preſented in anſwer; A cloud of miſapplied Scriptures we hope will deceive none but the ſimple. We are willing to believe that God hath, and will give you a better underſtanding, then to be deceived with vain words. <hi>Watch you, ſtand faſt in the faith, quit your</hi> ſelf well like a ſolid Chriſtian, be ſtrong: If you doubt of any thing, ſend to us, we ſhall endevor to give you ſatisfaction, and ſhall beg of God to guide you, even he himſelf by his Spirit, into all Truth: Appear not in any other meetings, as you tender the welfare of your Soul, tempt not God to, leave you. If your Husband bring them to your houſe, get from among them. If by any means you can, have no diſcourſe with them, leaſt you be enſnared. You are warned in your Husband, he converſed with them, and how ſoon is he become one of them, as his Letter ſhews, We pitty his condition greatly. What would we do to recover him, and bring him out of ſuch ſnares? But we fear leaſt ſome ſin is unrepented of, and that God is offended, and hath left him; Look you to your ſelf, and paſt wayes, and know the evil you have done, and meet the Lord by faith and timely Repentance; It may be God will be gracious to you, and you ſhall be kept in the fire, and in the water, in the midſt of the greateſt and neareſt dangers; ſo that they ſhall not touch you, nor hurt you. Which ſhall be the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of thoſe who are true friends to your ſoul, and do watch over you, as thoſe who muſt give an account to God for you.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Farewell.</salute>
                  <signed>From the Elders, and ſome brethren of the Church of Chriſt, meeting at <hi>Stoppors,</hi> In the name, and on the behalf of the reſt. Sam. Eaton.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:166753:43"/>
               <head>The Quakers Reply to our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned anſwer, ſent by <hi>Richard Waller,</hi> with an injunction that it ſhould be read in the preſence of the CONGREGATION.</head>
               <p>I Have received a Letter, wherein I find many buſie minds, giving ſenſes upon the Scriptures, and falſe Accuſations.</p>
               <p>Can you give a better ſenſe upon the Scriptures then they are? thereby you ſhew another Spirit then that which did give forth the scriptures. For all Scriptures being given forth by the Inſpiration of the ſpirit, it is of no private Interpretation, nor came not by the will of man. O fleſh be ſilent before the Lord, who art giving ſenſes, and ſpeakeſt with thy own will: wherein thou haſt uttered forth thy ſolly, who art unlearned: therefore thou art wreſting the Scriptures, which thou wouldſt turn up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the backs of others, and the ſame turns upon thy own back and pate, who art giving ſenſes: who liveſt in the corrupt nature, and pleadeſt for it, a ſervant to the Devil, maintaining his Kingdom: Whereof thou Accuſeſt him being led Captive, and thou art led Captive, doing the work of the Devil, and art a witneſs againſt him, or them who are in the ſecond Birth, and the children of the living God: <hi>Jacob</hi> was a perfect man, God ſaw no iniquity in him; <hi>Iob</hi> was a perfect man; And God ſaw no tranſgreſſion in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and Chriſt ſaid, <hi>be ye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, as your heavenly father is perfect:</hi> and the Apoſtle ſaid, ſee that you ſtand perfect in the will of God, <hi>And he that is born of God ſinneth not, neither can be ſin, becauſe the ſeed of God
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:166753:43"/> remains in him; he that doth righteouſneſs is righteous, even as he is righteous; let no man deceive you with vain words,</hi> and in that number you ſhew your ſelves to be deceiving with vain words; <hi>and we ſpeak wifdom among them that are perfect,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle; Yet not the wiſdom of this world, that cometh to nought: but in the wiſdom of the world thou art, witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing againſt that which the Apoſtle juſtified, and haſt raiſed thy ſelf out of that which he was in, giving Senſes and Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings upon his words, as they painted Serpents did, ſhewing a contrary Spirit then the Apoſtles had; Shewing thy ſelf in the firſt Birth, and not in the ſecond, which is perfect; Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally learned, but not Spititually, that which will own it, own without any Witchcraft, Sorcery, or twining humane in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, or its ſence upon the Scripture, which all is for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and Fire; For to that in thy Conſcience do I ſpeak, which ſhall eternally witneſs for me, and before you witneſs, the ſame Spirit that gave forth the Scriptures, you muſt wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs theſe things in your ſelves. The contradiction is in your ſelves, and a ſeeming contradiction, and not in the Scripture: Therefore it is you that look after the ſenſe of the word, which cannot own it as it is, and ſo make the contradictions; had you the Spirit which <hi>Paul</hi> had, and which gave forth the Scriptures, you would not wreſt it to your own deſtruction; but the confuſion is in your own minds, and that is wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures in you, and giving ſenſes to it, which is for deſtruction; And whereas you ſpeak of <hi>Pauls</hi> condition; I deſire you to let <hi>Pauls</hi> condition, and the Saints alone: For you know nothing of them, but are giving ſenſes upon their words, and wreſting them, being uneſtabliſhed with his Spirit, and his life, and the Saints; For that mind in you hath nothing at all to do with it: The Letter ſaith that the Saints were compleat in him, and is not upright perfect? Wherein it ſhews that you are not compleat in Chriſt, but without in the world, giving meaning to his words; whereas you ſpeak of giving a particular expoſition of every Quotation, it is the buſie mind which would be exalted; So if I ſhould anſwer to every ſenſe which you have given upon the Scripture from your conceivings, I ſhould make fools wiſe in their conceits,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:166753:44"/> which God hath promiſed, he will ſcatter the proud in their imaginations, and there you are, and there is your por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Friends, Your weakneſs you have uttered, while any one thinks they are perfect they cannot tell; but are in the ſame mind that you are in, giving ſenſes upon the Scripture, which was given forth by an eternal ſpirit, and you are giving ſenſes upon ir, with your external minds, and your own imagined wiſdom, which is from below, you utter it forth; for it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies perfection, and while your minds ſtand in imitation, there is an Image in your minds, which ſets ſomething up in it, that neither knows Chriſt, nor the way, nor the Scripture; Neither can it refolve doubtfull minds; But that ſenſe giving upon the Scriptures doth heal up the beaſt which hath a wound, and applies the Scriptures to a wrong nature, to your own ſenſe, that thereby many are led blind by you, and led into doubts, and inſtead of ſtabliſhing, you unſtabliſh, and that is it which keeps ſo many in ſin, and from waiting upon Jeſus Chriſt, which comes to take away ſin.</p>
               <p>Friends, here you ſit as Judges of the Saints conditions, ſpeaking you do not know what of the Goſpel, of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, of Juſtification, and Sanctification, which of theſe things you know nothing of, but are buſie minds, uttering forth your folly; for none of theſe things can you witneſs, which you ſpeak of, not the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor Juſtification, nor Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, nor the Goſpel, not in the inward man, but in the Notion; he that is ſanctified is juſtified, and witneſſed, and where it is not, it is babled and diſputed upon, as you do, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your own imaginations and ſenſes upon it, which leads in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to temptations from God, both your ſelves and others; By one offering he hath for ever perfected them that are Sanctified.</p>
               <p>Friends, give over your babling, and ſee which of you can witneſs this Chriſt, this Sanctification, and this Perfection, and give over your diſputes, and rabling, and rambling with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean mind; For the Grace of God teaches to deny all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs and worldly luſts. Which I do ſee you know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of but in the Notion, and the Hiſtory of it, who are Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Letter.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:166753:44"/>
               <p>Friends, ſee if you be brought to ſee a Conſcience that doth accuſe for ſin; For that you muſt witneſs before you witneſs the Goſpel, and look within your ſelves, and gad not abroad; For that is the woman that abides not in her own houſe.</p>
               <p>Friends, let me ask you one queſtion, are you come to the end, that you are Teachers of others? I believe it will appear with a literal knowledge; or have you an infallible judgement to judge of perfection, who were perfect, and who were not perfect? For you make it appear as though you were able to judge, but it is with your own ſenſe, and dark thoughts, and not with the ſpirit that gave forth the Scriptures, who was the Miniſter of Chriſt which had it; ſaid that they might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent every man perfect in Chriſt Jeſus; You ſpeak forth your imaginations; Is the perfection that is in the Saints, but a kind of perfection as you ſpeak of? Theſe are your Saints which live in the Imaginations, and your Perfection, and your Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which is your own ſenſe, who wreſt the Scripture to your own deſtruction; by one offering he hath for ever perfected them that were ſanctified: out of your own mouths you are judged. Friends, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did not tell you theſe words, but you are theeves that ſteal his words; For he ſpoke to the Saints which had an underſtanding, when he bad them forget thoſe things which were behind, which you need not give a ſenſe to his words, and wreſt them to another meaning; that is your condition which <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks of, for you live in the nature by whom Offences come; that is but a form, and the Robber to apply his words, except you had a Principle within you that told you ſo: And <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>if they ſay they have no ſin, they deceive themſelves, and the truth is not in them;</hi> But ſaith he, <hi>if you confeſs your ſins, he is faithfull and juſt to forgive,</hi> and to clenſe from all ſin; and if you walk in the light as he is in the light, the blood of Jeſus, Chriſt cleanſeth from all ſin; But here you are not in this light, onor cannot witneſs this blood, no not the confeſſion of your ſin, but in the generation of the Phariſees, gathered Churches, ſeparated from others, contending againſt Chriſt; Who ſaid, <hi>a good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit,</hi> and witneſſed a good Conſcience before <hi>Pontius Pilate:</hi> and where Chriſt is made manifeſt, he hath
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:166753:45"/> deſtroyed the works of the Devil; and he that is born of God ſinneth not, and he that ſinneth is of the Devil; Hereby are the children of God known from the children of the Devil; And in that Generation you are pleading for the ſin, and not for the faith, which purifies the heart; But that mind and ſervant muſt ſerve its own maſter, whom you contend for; So every kingdom ſtands for it ſelf, yet you have one of the beaſts colours of profeſſion, which makes you to appear beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull, as ever the Harlot did, under a pretence of the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, which is a ſtranger from the Spirit of God, as you utter it forth, which the Saints were guided by.</p>
               <p>Friends, you give Expoſition of the Apoſtles words, which he gave no ſuch expoſition, but ſpake plainly; he was a perfect man that could bridle his own tongue; and I know none in your Church and Generation can do it; Herein thou ſheweſt thy ſelf and thy Religion to be vain: For he that hath not power over his own tongue, his Religion is vain, and thy ſelf no Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Chriſt; For he was a Miniſter of Chriſt that ſaid ſo, but you are evil beaſts, and ſlow bellies, which the Scripture ſpeaks of; Are they not hirelings, as the Prieſts were? are they not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of men maſters? and have they not the chiefeſt place in the aſſemblies? are they not lyars, which pretend to be in the ſame ſtate the true Prophets were in? you are in the ſame nature which juſtifies them, who are for condemnation, and God will condemn that high wiſdom of yours; the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>as he is, ſo are we,</hi> in this preſent world: which of you can witneſs that there is no hole for Satan? But friends, look within, and you ſhall ſee he keeps the houſe, you plead ſo much for him; Friends, in that life you live in, you cannot ſee it, <hi>For none can ſee God and live:</hi> therefore are you blinded, Fogged, and Miſted with the corruptions of the dark mind: therefore take the alaſs, alaſs, to your ſelves, and pitty your own ſelves: he that believes is born of God, and he that is born of God ſinneth not, and he that is born of God overcomes the world, and this belief you ſhut your ſelves out of, and do make it appear that you do not believe, to that in your Conſciences I ſpeak.</p>
               <p>Friends, as touching <hi>Johns</hi> words, let fleſh be ſilent for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:166753:45"/> ſenſes upon them, for that fills the world full of imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and fancies: For you are the Lyars, which would draw ſomething out of his words, and give another meaning to them, and ſhew a contrary ſpirit, and the wreſting of the Scriptures; but all ſuch as you are diſcovered, where the life of them is made manifeſt, who wreſt the Scriptures, and give your own ſenſe and meaning upon them, and ſo bewitch them by your craft, and draw them from waiting upon God to have them fulfilled: ſo that mind judgeth all to be deceit, which is not according to your own lenſe, and ſo calls light darkneſs, and evil good: Friends, you ſtrengthen your ſelves with that Scripture, <hi>as he that ſaith he hath no ſin, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives himſelf, and the truth is not in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here you ſtand up for the Devils kingdom, For you have not confeſſed your ſins yet; <hi>If you confeſs you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſin, he is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>and juſt to forgive, and to cleanſe from all ſin;</hi> but theſe thinge you know nothing of, but ſhew forth your corrupt mind, and your ſelves of them which the Scripture ſpeaks of.</p>
               <p>Friends, here you have uttered forth your folly without knowledge and underſtanding, and make it appear that you never heard the voice of God, for his voice ſhakes the Earth; Firſt you muſt witneſs the Earth ſhaken, before you witnes the Heavens; and make it appear, that an your knowledge is notionary and earthly, and yet ſtanding, and of this World; and the world by their wiſdom know not God, and there you are: to that in your conſcience I ſpeak; here you thruſt your ſelves out of the Church of God, and ſhew forth your ignorance, not having the form of the Letter; For <hi>Paul</hi> when he came among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> he was with them in fear, and weakneſs, and much teembling, that their Faith might ſtand in the power of God, and not in the wiſdom of Words; but here are you not: and the <hi>Corinthims</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>Titus</hi> trembling: and he that was a Miniſter of Chriſt, exhorted the Saints <hi>to work out their ſalvation with fear and trembling, for it was God that wrought both the Will and the Deed;</hi> and the Aſſembly which aſſembled to <hi>Ezra,</hi> had all trembling hearts, and <hi>Iobs</hi> fleſh trembled, and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> fleſh trembled, and his bones quaked, and <hi>Moſes</hi> when
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:166753:46"/> he heard the voice of God, he trembled; &amp; <hi>Habbakuk</hi> when he heard the voice of God, he trembled. <hi>Hear the word of the Lord all you that tremble at his Word;</hi> when your Brethren hate you and caſt you out and ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Lord he glorified, he ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to your joy when they ſhall be aſhamed; and in that Generation you ſhew your ſelves to be, not knowing the Power of God not the Scriptures, but err; ſo ſhutting your ſelves out, from the life of them that gave forth the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, making your ſelves openly to appear blind; Friends, beſilent, as giving ſenſes of ſhaking and of removing of things without you; for, it is the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th within you, and the Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons within you which plead for the Devils kingdom ſo much, which muſt be removed, and that bufie minds which are giving ſenſes upon the Saints Conditions, for eternally you know nothing. Friends, as touching <hi>Moſes</hi> Condition, when any one witneſſestlie, ſame Condition, you cannot own it, but are cavelling about words; neither can you witneſs that you are made free from the Law, <hi>for the Law hath power over a man as long as he lives;</hi> The Saints that did witneſs they were made free: from the Law by the body of Chriſt, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed this quaking and trembling, which you with your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine wiſdom would give ſenſes upon them, and deſpiſe: but he ſhall not enter into the Kingdom: Did not <hi>Habbakuks</hi> lips tremble; and his belly quake? And did not the Prophets knees knock together and quake? <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Ioh,</hi> their fleſh trembled, and ſo muſt all proud fleſh he laid low, and the loftineſs of man be brought down and your imaginations, and God alone be exalted; the power that makes you to quake and tremble is now made manifeſt, which you know not; for if you did, you would not give ſo many ſenſes upon the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; and the ſame Power is now made manifeſt as ever was, praiſed be the Lord for ever; As they that ſaw the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of the Viſion, as you ſpeak, ſo you ſee the outſide of the Letter, and would flie from them who have the power of the Letter, as <hi>Daniel</hi> had; ſo you ſee the outſide, but not the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, as <hi>Daniel</hi> did, if you did, you would not utter forth your ſolly, ignorance and weakneſs: the ſame Chriſt they do witneſs to be made manifeſt, that makes proud fleſh to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:166753:46"/> tremble, and the ſame operation and death to be brought conformable to Chriſt they witneſs: but this power working in them as thou ſayeſt thou knoweſt not, and whereof you ſpeak, that you know them whom God ſpake to by Angels and Viſions, whom he wrought wonders by, but only by a hiſtory-knowledge by Paper and Ink, and there you ſhew your ſelves to be lyars; for them whom you do accuſe, which you call Quakers, the wonderous Works of the Lord are made manifeſt among them; though that Chriſt wrought Miracles among the people, yet they ſaid, he did it by <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub</hi> the Prince of Devils; and thou ſheweſt thy ſelf to be in the ſame Adulterous Generation that the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees were, which would have a ſign or a wonder, but there in none ſhall be ſhewed to thee but the ſign of <hi>Jonas;</hi> for an adulterous Generation ſeeks for a ſign, and there thou art. Friends, you ſay there is nothing in all the Scriptures, makes out of the people meeting together as concerning trembling; did not the <hi>Corinthians</hi> tremble when <hi>Titus</hi> came to preach among them? and did not the Aſſemblies that came to <hi>Ezra</hi> tremble? there is nothing in your minds of God, born up in your underſtandings to judge withall; ſo in your'own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits you are ſatisfied; and doth not the Lord ſay, <hi>I will ſhake all Nations; and let all the Inhabitants of the Earth tremble;</hi> ſo ye ſhew forth the ignorance of the form, for the power of it you cannot own, nor believe where it is operating and working; Friends, you have uttered forth many lyes and ſlanders, and ſcandalous ſpeeches; lay your hands upon your mouths, bluſh and be a ſhamed, who art in <hi>Cains</hi> nature, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the righteous ones in your hearts, and ſpewing forth your venome againſt a harmleſs people; was it not the practice of the Saints to wait alone upon God for counſel, for wiſdom, for grace, and for the Spirit? and being guided by the light of God they waited upon God; and the Apoſtle exhorts them, <hi>that they ſhould take heed to the light within them, until the day dawn, and the day-Star ariſe in their hearts;</hi> and no Propheſie of the Scripture came by the Will of man, ſo it was of no private Interpretation, <hi>but Holy men ſpake as they were moved by the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> this moving you ſpeak
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:166753:47"/> not from, neither know; therefore as dogs, fnarle and bite them who are guided by the ſame Spirit, and wait for the ſame Spirit, by which we have unity with them in the ſame Spirit; and you ſhew your ſelves to be in the number of them who uſe their tongues, and ſay, he ſaith, when ſaith the Lord, I never ſpoke to them; but you ſpeak a vain divinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your own brain, and not from the mouth of the Lord, gathering your ſelves together againſt the Lord and againſt his annointed; but I am ſatisfied, that I ſee your fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and weakneſs uttered forth, which doth blind many; but God is raiſing up a light which will diſcover you; the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of God they own, but your Doctrine which is of man, they deny; And if theſe be your Ordinances which you ſpeak of, as ſprinkling Infants, and telling people of a Sacrament, theſe we deny, for God never commanded them; and if you draw people to theſe things which God never command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, you bewitch them; for the <hi>Galathians</hi> were bewitched, which were drawn to act theſe things, God had not comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded when the ſubſtance was come; &amp; ſo you do bewitch them to follow your Traditions from the ſight of God within them. And as touching Magiſtrates, you are falſe accuſers which the Scripture ſpeaks of, which have the form and not the power; For all who are brought into the Truth, do la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with ſingleneſs of heart unto God, and not with eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervice; and their ſouls are ſubject to the power of God, and Juſtice they own, and honour in their ſoul, which cuts down filthineſs and corruptions which are alive in you, which makes you to give forth ſo many falſe accuſations upon a harmleſs people, who wait for the reſtoring of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the overturning the World and the Kingdoms of it, and the Image of the Devil defaced in man, and the Image of God renewed in Righteouſneſs, and man brought into his being from whence he was fallen; and ſo you are yet under the dominion of Satan, judging truth errour and blaſphemy as ever they did, which had the form and not the power, in whoſe ſteps you walk; ſeeing you have uttered forth your folly ſo and filthineſs, and call your ſelves the Church of Chriſt; his Church is not a ſinful Church, for that
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:166753:47"/> you ſtand up for; but his Church which he hath purchaſed with his blood, is without ſpot or wrinkle, or any ſuch, and yours is but an imitation; therefore ſlander not the Church of Chriſt, <hi>as they which ſay they are Iews, and are not, but are Synagogues of Satan;</hi> and there you are.</p>
               <p>I charge you by the Lord, that you read this among all your Churches as you call it, and as you will anſwer it before the Lord, for to that in your Conſcience do I ſpeak.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>From ſome Friends in the Truth, whom the World calls Quakers in <hi>Lancaſhire.</hi>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="annotations_to_letter">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:166753:48"/>
               <head>Annotations upon this Reply, and an Extraction of the unſavory paſſages contained in it.</head>
               <p>THe greateſt part of this Reply contains nothing but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull and villifying expreſſions, and is extremly cenſorious of us, as of perſons who have nothing but darkneſs in us, and is ſelf-magnifying, as conceiving themſelves onely in the light, and having themſelves, and they onely the ſpirit. And ſome ſmall part of it makes mention of the very ſelf ſame Scriptures which <hi>Richard Wallers</hi> Letter doth contain, and of ſome few more of like nature; But there is ſcarce the ſhew of an anſwer to any thing in ours, though it be very large and tedious; Some of the un-favory and un-Chriſtian expreſſions, I have gathered out and preſented to publike view, that all perſons that have to do with them, may know what ſcurrilous language they may expect inſtead of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I find many buſie minds giving ſenſes upon Scripture.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O fleſh be ſilent before the Lord, who art giving ſenſes.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who ſpeaks with thine own will.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou haſt uttered forth thy folly.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who are unlearned, therefore thou art wreſting the Scriptures.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The ſame turns upon their own back and pate.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou liveſt in corrupt nature, and pleadeſt for it.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A ſervant to the Devil, maintaining his Kingdom.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou art led Captive doing the work of the Devil.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou art a witneſs againſt him and them who are in the ſecond birth.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:166753:48"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou art deceiving with vain words.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In the wiſdom of the world thou art.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shewing a contrary ſpirit to the Apoſtle.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shewing thy ſelf in the firſt birth, and not in the ſecond.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Litterally learned, but not ſpiritually.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Had you the Spirit, you would not wreſt Scripture to your own deſtruction.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The confuſion is in your own minds.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let</hi> Pauls <hi>condition alone, for you know nothing of it.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You are not compleat in Chriſt, but without in the world.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It is the buſie mind that would be exalted.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If I ſhould anſwer to every ſenſe you give, I ſhould make fools wiſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>God will ſcatter the proud, and there you are, and there is your portion.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Your exernal mind, and imagined wiſdom, which is from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>There is an Image in your mind, which neither knows Chriſt, nor the way, nor the Scripture.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That ſenſe giving, heals up the beaſt that hath a wound.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here you ſit as Judges of the Saints conditions, ſpeaking you do not know what of the Goſpel, of Moſes, of the Law, of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of Sanctification.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of theſe ye know nothing, but have buſie minds uttering forth your folly.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>None of theſe can you witneſs to, not the Law, not</hi> Moſes, <hi>not Juſtification, not Sanctification, not the Goſpel in the inward man, but in the Notion.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It is babled and diſputed upon as you do.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Friends, give over your babling.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Give over your diſputing, and rabling, and rambling with an unclean mind.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Look to your ſelves, and gad not abroad, for that is the woman thae abides not in her own houſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Paul <hi>did not tell you theſe words, but you are thieves and ſteal his words.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You live in that nature by whom offences come.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But here you are not in this light, nor can witneſs this blood, nor the confeſſion of your ſin.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:166753:49"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You are in the Generation of the Phariſees contending againſt Chriſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Children of the Devil, and in that Generation are ye plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for ſin, and not for faith.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You have one of the beaſts colours of profeſſion.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You appear beautifull as every harlet doth.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>None in your Church and Generation can bridle his tongue;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Herein thou ſhewſt thy ſelf and thy Religion to be vain.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You are evil beaſts, and ſlow bellies.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You are Blinded, Fogged, Miſted with the corruptions of a dark mind.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You are liars which would draw ſomthing out of</hi> Johns <hi>words.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here you ſtand up for the Devils Kingdom.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You have uttered forth your folly without knowledge.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The world by wiſdom knows not God, and there are you.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You are in the ſame nature, who juſtifie them who are for condemnation.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The earth within is that which pleads for the Devils King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou ſheweſt thy ſelf to be of the ſame Adulterous Generation of the Scribes and Phariſes.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You have uttered forth many lyes, and ſlanders, and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſpeeches.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You are in</hi> Cains <hi>nature, murthering the righteous one.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You are ſpewing forth your venom againſt an harmleſs people.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As dogs, ye ſnarl and bite them that are guided by the Spirit of God.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You ſpeak a vain divination.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You are yet under the dominion of Satan.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You have uttered forth your folly and filthineſs.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They that ſay they are Iews, and are not, but are of the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Satan, there are you.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <p>This is ſome of that mire and dirt, which as the Sea they caſt up againſt us, meerly for the cauſe of that Letter which we ſent to one of their wives, who ſtood related to us; But this is not all, for the whole Reply conſiſts of ſuch kind of Language, ſave that here and there, there is ſome ſmall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:166753:49"/> of ſome Scriptures produced for the Juſtification of Perfection anh Quaking, which I ſee no cauſe to return any further anſwer to, becauſe the anſwer that is already given in the Letter that we ſent, which is now preſented to publike view, may be equally applied to ſuch Scriptures which are here added, as to thoſe other Scriptures which I met with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and will remain in like force.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the perſons, who alone pretend to the Spirit, and to the ſecond birth, and do not onely lay us, but all the Saints in all the World, under the condemnation of ſuch who have not the ſpirit, and are in the firſt birth, and not in the ſecond. But what ſpirit it is, that Dwells, and Acts, and Rules in them, doth appear from their expreſſions, for their ſpeech bewraies them.</p>
               <p>Theſe things have I preſented for this end and purpoſe, to obſtruct their way, and ſtop their further proceedings, that by their impoſtures they may pevail no longer; If God ſhall be pleaſed to give his bleſſing to my endeavors, herein it will be a good reward of my labors; however I have diſcharged my duty, and ſhall have peace in that.</p>
               <p>There was a paper given unto me, containing the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Iohn Gilpin</hi> a Quaker; Which is now printed for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like view, that all may take notice what ſpirit it is that poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth theſe perſons, and may fear and tremble at Gods juſt Judgements, who delivers up them to Satan, who caſt off him.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:166753:50"/>
            <head>
               <hi>There is lately Printed and ſold by</hi> Thomas Brewſter, <hi>at the three Bible in</hi> Pauls <hi>Church-yard, near the Weſt and, theſe Books,</hi> viz.</head>
            <p>A diſcovery of Myſtical Antichriſt, Diſplaying Chriſts Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but attempting to lay waſte Scriptures, Churches, Chriſt, Faith, Hope. &amp;c. Containing an examination of the Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines and ways of the Quakers in <hi>York-ſhirie;</hi> Written by, <hi>John Pomroy, Pa. Gliſſen, Ioſeph Kellet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Milk for. Babes in Chriſt, or Meditations, Obſervations, and Experiences: Divers Caſes of Conſcience Reſolved, &amp;c. by <hi>M. Fynch,</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel in <hi>Lincoln-ſhire,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sions glory Diſcovered in the Churches and Ordinances, before the fulneſs of the <hi>Iews</hi> come in by <hi>I. Prowd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three Treatiſes, 1. A Diſcovery of the unſupportable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of ſin. 2. The Reſolution of a ſoul to return to God, that is ſenſible of his withdrawings. 3. The Entertainment that ſuch meet within their returnings, by <hi>P. Hobſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reſurrection of the Witneſſes, and <hi>Englands</hi> fall from <hi>Rome,</hi> by <hi>M. Cary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Refractoria Diſputatio:</hi> Or the Thwarting Conference, In a Diſcouſe between different Intereſts: Diſputing about the Diſſolution of the late Parliament, and other Changes of State.</p>
            <p>A ſtop to the mad multitude, being an Anſwer to a ſcurrilous book, publiſhed againſt the peace of this Commonwealth: Entituled, <hi>The Grand Politick Informer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Deſcription of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> as it flouriſhed in Chriſts time; With a large Map, Explaining, 268. places therein, and in the Suburbs thereof; ſhewing the ſeveral places of the Acts and ſufferings of Jeſus Chriſt, and his holy Apoſtles; As alſo of the Kings and Prophets, &amp;c. Alſo ſeven general Rules for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding Scriptures that ſpeak of Chriſts coming, and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and calling the <hi>Iews.</hi> by <hi>H. Jeſſey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vindicae Juſtificationis Gratuitae,</hi> Juſtification without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, or the free Juſtification of a ſinner, and the abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the New Covenant Explained, Confirmed, and Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated, from the Exceptions, Objections, &amp;c. Caſt upon it by the aſſerters of conditional Juſtification, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Woodbridge,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cranford,</hi> By <hi>W. Eyre,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel, and Paſtor of a Church at <hi>New-Sarum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
